okay in the three minutes i have
i cannot speak as fast as you just did
so i won't even try
i'll try to make a couple of basic
points
every economic system in the history of
the world
displays the following pattern is born
it evolves over time and then it dies
and passes away
giving way to another one and part of
that process has always been
the conviction of the people in each
economic system
that sooner or later they can they
should
and they will do better overcome some of
the problems and difficulties they're
facing
and organize a system that better meets
human needs the process is sometimes
relatively smooth other times it's rocky
that varies with the conditions and
particularly with the level of
resistance
from those who don't want to see the
system change
and shift capitalism in my
judgment has been born most would agree
has evolved over the last three
centuries
or so and is now at that last
stage the only question now is exactly
how and when the passing
occurs likewise
in my judgment the yearning for
something better
has built up in capitalism
to a pretty intense level now
whether you look at the debts of
students
whether you look at the mind-bending
inequality
that this system generates over and over
again
unless and until it is revolted against
by masses of people who do something
about the inequality only to discover
that as long as capitalism remains the
tendency to inequality
resumes i think people are also tired
of the instability every four to seven
years
capitalism crashes we've had three
in this new century in its 20 years
yup right on schedule every four to
seven years
millions lose their jobs businesses go
belly up
cities and towns can't get the revenue
they need to provide the services
we depend on one sign of the exhaustion
of this system
a level of money creation a level of
debt creation
we have never seen government debt
corporate debt
personal debt the system is exhausted
and the entire private enterprise system
is now
on 24 7 government life
support i think it's over i think that's
difficult for us all to live through
and we better learn some lessons from
the british empire
from which they have been tumbling for a
century
we could and should do better on the
downswing
than the british have been able to and
the more we talk about it
and discuss it and explore it the better
our chances
to make another progressive transition
to a better system that we all need and
will
benefit from
okay destiny are you keeping us on a
timer
i am all right as of march 2021
americans rank the economy
job markets the handling of the
coronavirus and leadership in washington
as the four most important challenges
facing
our country socialist policies would not
alleviate any of these concerns
countries have tried the socialist
experiment time and time again this has
failed
doctors in cuba moonlight is taxi
drivers countries with socialized health
care haven't fared much better than the
us and their handling of the coronavirus
and any socialist regime will
necessarily involve the bureaucracy of
washington even more heavily in our
economy
any country that has attempted to
realize a fully socialist economy has
either failed completely such as in the
case of the ossr
destroyed large swaths of their economy
such as in venezuela or been forced to
embrace more neoliberal economic
policies to realize true growth in their
economy
such as in china or vietnam liberal
market policies work better in both
theory and practice when it comes to
efficiently allocating resources to
maximizing
the economic productivity of any country
and we've seen this play out time and
time again
across a wide variety of markets and
countries throughout history across the
globe
oftentimes people like richard wolff
will bring up the boom bust cycle as
though it's an inherent flaw of
capitalism but i believe i speak for
most when i say that a boom bust cycle
is preferable to just going bust as so
many socialist countries have
it's also important for us to realize
that no economic organization is in and
of itself inherently more
immoral but rather we ought to view them
as tools to effect some greater output
for our country
that we can later utilize and distribute
in the most fair manner with government
policy to most of our citizens as we see
fit
creating a bigger a bigger pie so to
speak from which all of us can eat
morality and justice should exist in the
realm of government policy we cannot
allow it to blind us to the economic
realities surrounding us
no matter how much we wish a wild lion
not to eat us our desire alone will
never satiate its appetite
while socialism may sound good in theory
the destruction would rot on the wealth
of our country and the oppressive
restrictions it would place on our
businesses would not help the vast
majority of americans
be foolish to enforce protectionists or
socialist policies on our economy while
major developing economies such as india
and china are moving in the exact
opposite direction having realized time
and time again the failures and
socialist planning
socialism implies two major things a
change in both the means and mode of
production the means of production
change in such a way to completely
disallow private investment or ownership
and a change in the mode of production
such that we no longer produce goods and
services for a profit
instead businesses are only started with
the approval of some governmental body
some kind of central planning with the
equal decision making and management of
every worker and the goods and services
produced in any society
are what some government body dictates
irrespective of market forces or the
wants and desires of the citizens
it's likely in the course of this debate
that my opponent will suggest we take
after nordic or western european country
setting that things like socialized
health care or subsidized education or
powerful programs that address many of
the underserved needs of americans today
while this is true i would like to
remind everyone that we've spent the
last decade reminding conservatives that
the government simply providing welfare
has
absolutely nothing to do with socialism
my opponent believes that strong social
safety nets and welfare programs are
important parts of the government
most liberals would welcome him with
open arms me included consequential
there are five major hurdles that no
socialist i've ever spoken to is
adequately addressed and they are as
follows
number one what level of violence is
acceptable for you to reach our social
estate
number two how do we decide which
businesses are allowed to exist in a
socialist society without allowing
private capital investment
three is any form of investment
whatsoever allowed in a socialist
society for an expansion of business
four how are labor markets determined in
a socialist society and five how do we
calculate which goods and services a
nation needs if we do away with the
commodity form
those are my five cool all right so
we're gonna do the open format now for
the next hour
um i don't think i'm gonna need to
moderate too much as long as both of you
just
say something and allow the other person
to speak and don't talk over each other
it should be fine
so uh i guess begin uh now
where do you want to start well let me
let my
can i respond to what was said yeah
um i find this a laughable caricature of
anything i've ever written or anything
that i understand
uh is part of this conversation and i
don't appreciate
being told what i think or what i say or
what i mean
or what i intend i can speak for myself
and that would just be fine if we could
allow each other to do that number one
number two
i have no idea what this silly remark
that i hear so
often is that no socialist society
has succeeded at anything i have no idea
what you're talking about
let me give you an example one of the
most important metrics used in the
economics profession
around the world to assess the
quote-unquote
success of an economic system is the
rate of economic
growth you measure gdp and you look at
how it grows
over time and then you compare one
country to another
to assess their relative success
not as societies because that's a vague
generality
but at this particular metric which we
use in economics
to measure economic growth over time
it's not the only metric but it's a
widely used one
so i'm now going to use it in the 20th
century
the fastest growing metric the fastest
growing
gdp in any country measured
was the soviet union and in the
21st century we're living in the fastest
growing gdp
in the world has been the people's
republic of
china this is not an endorsement of one
or another
economic system it's a statement of fact
verified by any reliable
source of information the un
the project in the university of
california berkeley and
others who keep track of this
so this has to be understood because in
much of the world
economic growth is a shared
objective and goal that these two
societies have
excelled at achieving number one
number two when it comes to socialism it
would be useful
if we all understood what the word means
rather than playing around with
caricatures
for example the notion that socialism is
all about what the government does
has been contested throughout the
history of
socialism and that idea is less
dominant within the socialist tradition
now than it ever was over the last 150
years
for example today one of the most
important
issues for socialists has to do
not with government regulation not with
government owning and operating
businesses not with these bugaboos of
bureaucracy and all the rest of it
but has to do with an objective of
transforming
the organization of production in a
factory in an
office in a store not to have a small
group of people the owner the board of
directors
the tiny little minority at the top that
is a dictatorial power
inside an enterprise making all the key
decisions that the employees
have to live with even though the
minority making those decisions
is not accountable to those employees
that's a socialism of transformation at
the micro
level about which very little could have
been discerned
in the comments preceding these if we're
going to talk about socialism
then we have to talk about what it means
to the people
pushing for it and urging it and those
people have
learned from the 20th and 21st century
just like those who pushed for
capitalism three centuries ago
learned from their early experiments how
to refine how to adjust
and how to change to pretend that that
didn't happen
to trade in old and shrinking
conceptions of socialism
may be good debating ploy but it doesn't
advance our understanding
of anything um okay if you want to be
easier to have a
more of a back and forth rather than um
the super long
monologues so we can respond each other
more if you're okay with that um
just for for a couple of things you said
so i'm trying not to miss you
i just talked slower than you oh yeah no
it's fine it's fine
um my understanding is that um in the
20th century there was a faster growing
economy than the ussr and it was japan
japan still exists today and the ussr
does not i understand that the ussr
did show a huge amount of growth but i
think it's odd to use that
as an example when socialists often
point to the evils of imperialism
and when you point out the fact that
everybody was heavily industrializing
around that time as well i don't think
it's fair to say that the ussr simply
grew on the merits of socialism
uh when there were so many other things
happening at the time and when it was
outgrown by another economy that was
but those are those are the facts i mean
you can play whatever games you want
the fact of the matter is that the
soviet union's performance in the 20th
century
completely outshines that of japan
there's no comparison
in 1917 when the soviet union begins
it is the poorest country in europe by
far
it then goes through 70 years of a lost
world war one of a civil war
of an agricultural collectivization and
of world war
ii which did more damage in russia than
in any other country
none notwithstanding that it was the
poorest country at the beginning of this
horrific story
it ends up in 1965 being the number one
competitor of the united states for
global hegemony
that's only because of its
number one status in economic growth
that achieved the overcoming of all
those horrific losses i'm not arguing in
favor of this or that about the soviet
union
but the fact of its achievement
is a staggering reality that you can
dance
around from here to tomorrow but it
doesn't go away
because it's inconvenient to confront it
and the same thing is true now
if you read pearl box novels about china
before the revolution you will hear
about a society
whose depth of poverty literally blows
your mind
and here they are about to surpass the
united states before the end of this
decade
and that was accomplished by a communist
revolution
and a government that has been run by a
communist
party to this day and yeah
for sure they cleverly opened their
society
up to capitalists to come and join them
but to imagine that the achievement of
the
chinese economy is purely due
to the private capitalists rather than
to the state
economy that's making believe because
you need to have an argument
that puts the success at the credit of
one or the other
the infrastructure the training of the
mass of people
everything that happened in china is as
much a product
of the planning and policies of the
communist government than of any other
factor
and that has to be recognized as well
and none of this is an endorsement
that society has strengths and
weaknesses it has things we can
criticize but we can't make it up
because it's inconvenient to face
the successes they've had and continue
to have
okay so i'm not saying that the ussr did
not grow a lot
obviously the ussr grew massively your
claim is not that the ussr grew
that's not what we're arguing about it's
whether or not the ussr grew at the rate
that it did
due to socialism a country that was
heavily involved in multiple famines
a country that heavily went from little
industrialization to a lot of
industrialization
and a country that engaged in a lot of
imperialistic practices
is a country that grew massively in the
20th century to say that
all of their growth or even the majority
of their growth was due to the
organization of their economy
and not due to factors that were
independent of that organization to say
otherwise that they wouldn't have grown
maybe at an even faster rate now they've
been a capitalist economy
um there would have to be some evidence
provided for that i don't believe that
that's ever been adequately demonstrated
on the contrary i believe some people
have argued
that that russia could have potentially
grown the ussr could have potentially
grown even faster had it abandoned some
of its more outdated
forms of trying to manage their economy
when we bring up
china china has grown a lot under
certain socialist policies for sure
when we look at china especially in the
80s and 90s china began opening itself
up to
massive growth when it comes to foreign
investment china's the number two
country in the world that allows for
foreign direct investment
and the coalescing of all of china's
state-owned the soes estate-owned
enterprises into a select few industries
and then the massive opening of foreign
investment into that country to give
other people more control over privately
owned businesses
has been what has caused the massive
explosion that we've seen of china in
terms of pulling people out of global
poverty
as you mentioned in the video that you
did for the grivel institute you
attribute that to socialist policies but
the thing that really pulled china into
the 21st century in terms of
economic success was the opening itself
up to foreign direct investment was the
opening itself up to other economies
being able to interact with them more
which are all neoliberal trade policies
these aren't these aren't people-owned
businesses these aren't businesses that
are ran by the workers these are
i mean if anything china is a government
that runs the business itself it's a
state capitalist
economy more so than any type of
socialist or communist economy to say
that a single party regime is
having the workers themselves making
decisions over how the any any
individual business is
is uh running i don't think it's fair to
say um i guess one
we're really real quick just finishing
we're just gonna understanding of china
just this last part the thing that
confuses me the most and the thing that
frustrates me the most i guess when i
have
discussions with socialists is socialism
feels like this like
this very amorphous ever transforming
idea of what it actually is
such that i don't even know why we use
the word anymore so i'm very glad that
you've acknowledged that mark's
in in through his labor theory value
analysis was absolutely flawed and was
an absolute failure i'm glad you've
acknowledged that
the way of analyzing not acknowledged
you're making this stuff up i've never
acknowledged anything of the work okay
well
as you don't even know the way you get
this well earlier you just said that we
shouldn't hold ourselves captive to the
thinking of thinkers in the 19th century
in terms of what socialism is so i
assume you've evolved
no no i didn't do that at all i told you
that socialism
has a variety of theories within it it's
a broad tradition
it had to be in 150 years since marx
wrote
his ideas have moved into every country
on this earth at different levels of
economic
and cultural and political life and of
course
those different people all found
something valuable
but they all made their own
interpretations this is a rich diverse
tradition it's as if you you're going to
decide
what it is i mean when i say these
things i never said that the
marxist theory isn't valuable that the
labor theory of value
doesn't apply if you read any of the
books and articles
i've punked out in my life you'd know
that the exact
opposite is the case
wait a minute i want to correct
something about china because you keep
repeating it
okay you know why private enterprise and
private capital flows into china
in the 80s and 90s because china had
transformed itself from a place where
nobody wanted to invest
to a place like now where everybody does
capitalist enterprises went there
because they had a well-educated
disciplined labor force at very low
wages
because they had built an extraordinary
infrastructure
because you had a growing level of
income
for people to buy things that's why
general motors
produces and sells more cars in china
than it does in the united states
the reason private capital went there
was because
they had before the arrival created
the institutions every other part of the
so-called third world
asia africa latin america who had
received since the second world war
massive amounts of foreign aid were
desperately trying to do
what the chinese were doing namely
develop their countries so that
foreign private investment would come
china didn't get any foreign aid because
they were communists
and the united states didn't give them
any but they did a better job than all
the countries who did get it
in order to get to the point of economic
development
where it became interesting for
capitalists in japan and europe to go
there you need to pretend for reasons i
do not understand
that all of the achievements i've just
described
didn't happen that somehow they don't
deserve the credit
look in the world of economics maybe
perhaps you're not familiar
we do exactly what you just said we
ought to do
we look at societies and say they have a
capitalist economic system how did they
do
and they have a socialist system with
the different meanings of that term
and how did they do and then we say
they're different and part not all part
of the story
is the different system and if i say to
you that the
socialist transition tradition has
multiple interpretations
let me assure you that the capitalist
tradition
does as well the leaders of saudi arabia
right now
call themselves capitalists
can i can i ask you when you say
socialist what do you what do you mean
when you say socialist then i'm trying
to understand what this means
can you give me like a cohesive
coherence right that's good no let me
answer
they're a variety i'll give you three
basic strains right now they don't
exhaust it but then we
enable us to have a conversation one
strain
you leave enterprises in the hands of
private capitalists
but you recognize that the capitalist
system is so
flawed for example in terms of
inequality
in terms of business cycle instability
that you give a role to the government
of
massive intervention rules regulations
laws you know let me give you some
examples
in france it's the law that once you
begin working
after graduating from high school or
college every employer has to give you
five weeks of paid vacation from the
beginning
nothing like that exists in the united
states but this is a society that won
that for its people by the way by
socialists who did that
and put that on the books as it is on
most european
countries and socialists do that
because they believe for them that
socialism is when the government comes
in and regulates that's one kind
here's a second kind these second kind
of socialists they don't believe it
works real well if you do that
it's not enough so they want to take a
different step
they want the government to come in and
actually own and operate
enterprises not merely regulate them
with rules
and laws then there's a third kind which
i stressed a few moments ago
which is not about the government
doesn't care all that much
whether the government runs an
enterprise or the private does
they can figure out map whichever one
works better let's be real
practical but for them what socialism
means
is the transformation of the everyday
life
of working people no longer do you go to
work with other people telling you what
to do
where to sit what machine to use what
raw material to work on
and at the end of the day you go home
and you've got nothing more to say
about what you poured your brains and
muscles into no no no
for these socialists like me the crucial
thing is to reorganize
the workplace to bring real democracy
can you believe it to the place where we
work
in a country that claims to be
democratic we don't have democracy in
the workplace
we have a tiny group of people telling
the majority what to do
fully unaccountable to that majority you
know if we really believed in democracy
this kind of socialism argues we would
recognize that that's where adults spend
most of their adult life
at work and if you really believe in
democracy
it should have been installed in the
workplace but
capitalism doesn't permit that the folks
at the top want to keep the power
to keep their inordinate wealth even at
the
expense of no democracy and of a growth
record
inferior to what russia did in the 20th
century
and what china is doing now and that's
an enormous
price to pay okay so if you want to talk
about the
two and three definitions of socialism
that would be interesting to me but i
only heard two
definitions of socials here number one
is just capitalism um i
i don't know when this like redefining
happened of taking capitalism plus
government intervention and calling it
wait let me let me finish
right i don't know why this was the case
that uh state intervention
into private markets to have some form
of regulation or some form of socialized
healthcare
or giving workers five weeks off became
socialism it's clearly not socialism
it's so not socialism that i think marx
himself even said that the state would
be heavily required
in maintaining capitalism uh more so
than i guess even marx was able to
foresee because he predicted a
revolution of the proletariat in his
lifetime
um the idea that the state intervening
and providing some sort of social
welfare or safety net
is is that's just strictly a capitalist
system with some government intervention
if we want to talk about the concept of
the government owning and operating
enterprises or
number three the idea is that the
workers themselves have some like worker
managed thing
i would be interested in discussing
either of those two options as i believe
all five questions i laid out initially
applied to them
but for number one i just i wholly
reject that as a form of capital as a
form of socialism if you believe it is
i'd be curious if you can tell me what
is the difference between
the the first thing you laid out and any
capitalist that acknowledges that some
level of government intervention is
necessary
and keeping the economy going i'd be
glad to explain it to you
the history of socialism gets going in
the middle of the 19th century
and at that time socialists began to
argue
that capitalism was over capitalism was
done
and and a better system was available
and should be pursued
and they had a whole bunch of ideas
about that
they were a relatively small group if
you know the history of marx and marxism
it begins
relatively small as the 19th century
progresses
it gets larger and larger and guess what
happens when that movement gets larger
debates begin to happen inside of it as
to what in the world
capitalism is and what in the world
socialism is and here we go
some of the people decided that
socialism
as a radically alternative system wasn't
in the cards could never happen in some
views
could only happen in a distant future
well what then did socialists
do in the meanwhile before a real change
of system
happened answer advocate for the
government to be taken over by universal
suffrage
the mass of people what institute of
socialism
that was if you like a step in that
direction
an early socialism if you like and by
the way there were big debates pro and
khan
within the socialist movement about this
but they settled to
understand let's call it one kind of
socialism
and that's what you have in western
europe in scandinavia
to this day socialist parties advocate
that
and the people in that society
often vote those folks into power i'll
give you an example
the government in portugal right now a
perfect example european country
the government of portugal is a
coalition of three political
parties the largest is the portuguese
socialist party
the second one is the portuguese
communist party and the third one is the
portuguese green party
they were elected as a coalition
government in 2016.
they were re-elected last year
parenthetically
if your audience members don't know
about this that's because you live in a
society
that doesn't tell you about this even
though it's public knowledge
to anyone interested in finding out
those
parties push a socialist agenda
by which they mean government rules and
regulations
you may not like to call it socialists
but the people
involved and millions of them around the
world
do the other kind of socialism broke
away from this first kind
in the aftermath of the soviet
revolution
they were in favor of taking that extra
step
socialism for them meant that the
government should take over and
operate enterprises at least the
industrial ones
maybe later the agricultural ones and to
underscore their distinction from the
other
socialists who just wanted government
rules regulations and controls
they gave themselves the name communist
that's the only difference between them
and it has been that way
for nearly a century now since the
russian revolution
and then there's this third one which
has to do with transforming the
workplace
those are all socialisms they argue they
debate
they have a rich literature we have lots
of empirical examples
of all three kinds in the world
and if people want to think about how
they work and what kind of society they
produce
there's loads of evidence there we don't
have to hypothesize
or pretend or demonize either because
really
it doesn't lend itself to that if you're
serious
okay first of all just because a
government calls itself socialist i
don't think that that's adequate to
define said government as socialist
right do you agree with it give another
fine you can have enough that's what the
debate is this is to
make up yourself one second yeah okay so
you we have to give destiny a chance to
speak as well wait well so my question
would be like in terms of opportunities
to
give uh yeah i guess i might would you
consider like for instance like the nazi
party would you consider that a
socialist party as they have socialism
in the name it doesn't seem like a good
no why not the minute you know anything
about the
the nazi party you don't understand that
would you say that portugal lives is
portugal a socialist economy
or do they have markets do they have
private investment
markets have nothing to do with
socialism okay can you tell me what is
your definition of capitalism then
i i just because when i ask you what
what is socialism to you i'm
like i understand that you can talk a
lot and you can tell me what other
people have considered socialism to be
but under your current definitions
for instance no no you haven't given me
your definition you've told me what
other thinkers and
other countries in the past your
definition is not what portugal does or
it's not with the portugal
portuguese socialist or communist
parties you're giving me what other
people or other thinkers have thought
what socialism is because
under your current definition number one
the democratic party in the united
states would be considered a socialist
party
because they're in favor of heavy
government intervention in terms of
climate change or health care
and i don't know if you would agree
would you agree that the democratic
party in the united states of america is
a socialist party or if they rebranded
themselves
okay so so it's clear then that the
naming mechanism alone isn't enough for
you because the nazi party obviously
called themselves socialists i don't
think many people me included would
consider themselves socialist
and it's obvious that there must be some
um there must be some outside definition
that you're alluding to
that when you call something socialist
so i'm just trying to figure out
what what is what can you tell me what
is capitalism here what does it mean
when an economy or or a society is a
capitalist economy what does that mean
to you
well let me answer i gave you three
definitions of socialism i told you they
weren't the only three
this is a debate that's been going on
inside socialism
and it's perfectly reasonable for me to
give you those three
it might be nice for you if there was
one you could cling to but that's not
the way it is
the tradition is too big too broad too
global
for there to be one definition as there
is in most
interesting things in the world and
certainly and then many
large organizations and large traditions
i did give you my own my own is focused
on the transformation
of the workplace it's more interested in
the micro
transformation than in the the macro
ones and particularly
skeptical about the power of the
government as having had some bad
consequences i want to learn from these
early efforts to build socialism
so that the future revolts against
capitalism
will have a better outcome than the ones
that we've already had
what does that happen let me finish they
achieved many things we want to hold on
to
and they made some mistakes we want to
avoid and that's exactly what it means
to learn from the past now let me
address the question
of capitalism here's what capitalism is
not distinguished by
and therefore is not useful as a
definition markets
slavery has markets it's a different
economic system
feudalism had markets for much of its
history that's not a definition
of capitalism that's unique capitalism
doesn't uniquely have markets
at silly free or controlled markets
which is all we've ever had in the world
the controlled kind
are as old as as plato and aristotle who
argued
over markets by the way both of them
opposed markets
and thought they were socially
destructive institutions
just for the as a footnote you might be
interested in
but capitalism is unique in one way
it's not a system that's unique in its
markets
quote-unquote free enterprises
those are as old as methuselah but here
is what's unique
earlier systems for example slavery
organized the production of goods and
services around a dichotomy
a slave and a master the master
owned all the equipment all the means of
production
and including the worker himself and
herself
he owned them and that was a very
unusual way of organizing things
but it existed for a long time did it
have markets
often did it sometimes exist without
markets
you bet then there's feudalism radically
different
no master no slave nobody's anybody
else's property
but you know how that works you have a
small group of lords at the top
and a mass of serfs at the bottom and
the way the system works
is that the serfs swear loyalty to the
lord
and the lord in return to the surf and
the whole thing is sanctified
in europe by the catholic church
okay can't wait for captain let me
finish then comes capitalism
it's not a master and a slave it's not a
lord and a serf
it's a completely different arrangement
it's a contract
it's an employer and an employee
they don't swear anything to one another
and neither owns
the other one but they enter into a
contract
in which the employer says i'm going to
give you a wage at the end of the week
you're going to give me your brains and
muscles for these hours
of these days and that's a deal we're
going to make
and that's how we organize production
that's the distinction
of capitalism no that's a lot of keys
it's that's like
you haven't given me a definition of
capitalism at all you've told me a bunch
of things that capitalism isn't and then
you've given me
a bunch of random collected facts of
history but none of these things
absolutely for instance when you talk
about how markets aren't unique to
capitalism that's great worker
management isn't unique to socialism
worker management can exist under a
capitalist system right now i know that
you like to talk about
mondragon a lot mondragon
we're gonna go one at a time here okay
so let this definition then we'll
continue when we talk about worker
managed firms or worker managed co-ops
these things exist under capitalism
what what do you okay well what are you
saying then can i hold on real quick i'm
sorry
can i get an explicit answer um that is
answered within the last 50 years
without going back into
feudalism or what the pope said or the
schism of the catholic church
i i just i want to know very concretely
without moralizing or loading anything
or without talking about something that
happened in 1850 what is capitalism to
you what just can you just tell me or
explain
what capitalism is because it sounds
like yeah yeah go ahead
any definition of anything is they
process
of separating it from that which it is
not
that's all any definition ever was but
we don't typically give
definitions by naming every single thing
that something is not okay
is you differentiate it from a cat
otherwise there's no way to do it
to differentiate and they give a
definition of capitalism
you have to distinguish it from that
which it
is not those other systems didn't use an
employer employee relationship
that is the core distinguishing quality
of capitalism slavery doesn't have that
feudalism doesn't have that
and i never used the phrase worker
management
managers are not what we're talking
about
owning and operating if you want a user
word
it's workers as their own boss workers
as their
own board of directors if you like you
can use the colloquialism in the united
states
that has existed throughout our history
a worker co-op
a cooperative one worker one vote
all decisions majority vote that doesn't
exist in capitalism
that exists in a different relationship
among the people at the workplace not
slavery not feudalism
and not employer employee because those
are different
people in each of those systems worker
co-op that's no longer the case
that's why it's a radically different
socialist
system unlike any of the others how can
you say that that's unlike any of the
others when co-ops can exist today
under capitalist economies slavery can
exist and did it i'm not answering my
question i'm not i don't wanna i wanna
show you the negative or of everything
i'm saying i'm just you're saying today
that this is a unique thing that exists
there's never been a problem in any
society of which we have historical
record
for different class structures different
systems to coexist
you're asking me a question as if it
were we
is this possible it's never been
anything other
than the norm but you're telling me that
in your society
or i could be wrong you can correct me
but it sounds like in your excited in
your society you would exclusively like
firms to be in the hands of workers
which would necessarily preclude
not at all so written that i've never
said it
you're just attributing things okay i'm
sorry i'm trying to train very hard i
don't know what you're saying but the
problems your answers are very
long-winded you're not really answering
my question so
am i to understand then that you are in
favor of a society
where workers have the option to vote on
and have control over the workplace but
there's also room for a private
investment and the government intervenes
in things like health care
or education is this like the type of
society you're aiming for
my guess would be that the transition
from capitalism to what i'm talking
about
would have long periods of time
typically where these different class
structures these different systems
coexist with one another okay that's
what we have today
no you you don't have it in anything
like the way i want it well how do you
want it what's different from your
vision than what we have today
well what we have today is predominantly
capitalist with smatterings of the other
i'm interested in having predominantly
socialist with smatterings of the other
and without that's the difference and
without disallowing private investment
or disallowing
individual owners how do you get there
private investment is a completely
different matter
you can have private investment and
worker co-op how
it exists what's the problem why would i
ever
why would i ever invest in a company
without gaining some amount of equity in
the company they have no obligation to
return to many profit i would never
invest in a co-op
why would you invest in you you invest
in in businesses in the united states
correct because let me finish hoping for
example for something called
a capital gain you hope that if you buy
the shares
and if the company does real well you
will be able to sell the shares at some
future point
to another investor at a higher price
correct if that company's growth is the
product of
its worker co-op organization you're
perfectly happy
if you can make an investment that grows
over time
but in your world those shares don't
exist and first of all there exists were
uh these kinds of enterprises exist in
the world so this is not a hybrid
they're not then they're not worker
co-ops by definition a worker
okay tell me my definition might be
incorrect so you can correct me
my understanding is that what makes
something a worker co-op or what makes
something employee owned
is that the means of production or
whatever firm you operate at
is wholly owned and operated by the
workers meaning that when profits are
generated by that company they're
returned to the workers and when
decisions are made about that company
those decisions are made by the workers
if that is the definition that we're
going by there is no room for private
investment there
right but that's the wrong definition
and not the one that operates in the
world give me your definition definition
of a worker co-op
is that the workers make the key
decisions
they are their own board of directors
they may make the decision
democratically
to raise capital for their business
by selling shares of course they could
do that
those shares would not allow the people
who own them
to do the steps that they can in
capitalism they would not for example be
able
to dictate who's the board of directors
because the workers themselves
are their own board of directors but
there's no problem with private
investment
there never was and my question is
we have this definition i just want to
hone in on this definition okay my
question is
why would any individual ever invest in
a company that does not have a fiduciary
responsibility to their investors
so for instance in your world if i were
to buy 20
of a co-op their workers tomorrow could
say you know what
we're all bored we don't want to do this
anymore we're going to move on we're
shutting the business down
and now i've just completely lost on my
investment because they have no
responsibility to me
because i have non-controlling shares of
the only shares you're selling are
non-controlling
why would any private investment ever
come in knowing that that co-op
never has an obligation to make a profit
or return a dividend to the investors
there's many companies i'm listed on the
stock exchange right now that pay no
dividends to their investors
here in the united states it's a normal
part of our no
absolutely not they might not pay
i'm talking about capital markets 101.
they might not pay a dividend
but they are then you're badly
the foundation of the stock market in
the united states is a returning
of capital to the people that are the
ones doing the investment in companies
now it might be the case as you
correctly point out
it might absolutely it might be the case
really yeah really
you're unaware you're you're most of the
most of the most dynamic companies in
this country
are selling stock to people to whom they
have
no responsibility legal or otherwise
to give them a dividend ever okay
professor do you believe that a dividend
is the only way that you can return
capital to shareholders
that's not the point that absolutely is
the point you made no you made the point
what is the company responsible for
the companies responsible to run the
company they are not responsible to give
money back whether it's dividend return
of capital or
any other way to the people who give
them the money
to buy shares absolutely people who give
are gambling they hope that they can
sell the shares
for more and they will sell the shares
to anybody who can buy them
the company's not responsible to buy
those shares the company's not
responsible for what price they can get
if they lose their shirt tough luck it's
not an obligation or a responsible
that's the way the law of this country
works
for the stock market and there's no
problem
in a worker co-op saying to investors
we're going to grow better than what you
can get from a capitalist enterprise
so buying a share of our stock will give
you a better shot to sell it at a higher
price
later and i can give you examples i
don't
of a company that did that just so you
can see why an investor would do it
i mean you really you can make the
theater of your hand and i'm not making
the problem is you're just you said
something that's just so on its face
absurdly incorrect about the
characterization of u.s capital markets
you do you not agree that there exists a
legally binding the sec
literally regulates fiduciary
responsibilities to investors i don't
like this trick you've pulled
by making it sound like let me finish
please let me finish let me finish let
me finish you've made it sound as though
i believe the only way to return capital
to shareholders
is through dividends that's absolutely
not the case that's one reading of it
you can return it via stock buybacks you
can return it
uh via increase in growth to do any of
that you absolutely you have a fiduciary
responsibility to your shareholders of
course you do
if you read if you take my advice i
teach these courses
if you read what fiduciary
responsibility means
it's an abstract generalization it can
be
easily demonstrated in thousands of
legal cases
that there is no obligation of any
material sort that they return money
to the people who invest in them it is
perfectly okay
to run your business as you think it
should best be done
short of a committing fraud or illegal
activity
and that would apply in any system the
investor is taking a
chance buying your shares in the hopes
of selling them at a higher price
it happens all the time and it would be
perfectly consistent
with workers who run their own
enterprises and are their own board of
directors
that's not a problem never was there's
nothing inconsistent
with private investment on the one hand
and
worker co-ops on the other now if you
have a worker co-op system
they might decide because we have
democracy now
that they don't want that that they
would like to be the owners
as well as the board of directors of
their own enterprise
that's possible that would be one of the
variations of worker co-op economic
systems
just like we have variations of
capitalist
systems so in a private business in the
united states if i invest my money in a
business a publicly traded business if
they were to cash out all of that money
just close the business down and run
you're telling me that in the united
states that company wouldn't be held
liable for scamming its investors
absolutely that company had a good
lawyer and showed that they made an
honest effort to have a business
and then it didn't work out and they
closed it down the investor would have
absolutely
no standing exactly you're right but you
used a word there an honest effort and
it's doing all the heavy lifting in that
statement of course
you absolutely must show a court that
you are making a good this is part of
your fiduciary responsibility you are
making a good faith effort
to return money that's what the worker
co-op
could easily do we're making a good
faith honest effort
to make a business and that business
requires us to do x
y and z and the private investor got
nothing to do
that happens every day that's not what a
worker co-ops maximizing for though
a worker co-op if by your definition
which is a democratically voted
uh organization is going to be trying to
take into account what their members are
voting for they might not vote in the
best interest of a shareholder
they might vote to do something
completely different understood by the
shareholder that then but that's my
interest
only only the most naive shareholder in
the united states believes
that the company's decisions are
intended to do the best for the
shareholder
i can show you 50 000 legal cases in
which that's not the case
and which it is contested in the courts
and you could have that in a workout
that's
great and i can show you that and i can
show you the dow jones the nasdaq and
the s p
500 we could go to the uk and look at
the ftse 250 the ftse one and i can show
you histories of markets where companies
do reliably over long periods of time
return profits whether in the form of
dividends or the increase in your share
price
to people that invest in those companies
i'm sure you can show me a lot of things
that happen
that are bad in capital markets where
companies uh scam people much because i
can show you bad things that happen like
famines under the ussr
but pointing out to a few bad actors
does not clear up the problem of the
fact that investing in a co-op
where the workers have no obligation to
return anything to an investment about
bad actors you're inventing these things
we were talking about
private investment and worker co-ops you
had made a statement that these somehow
couldn't coexist
i'm explaining to you that there's not
the slightest problem
you want to change the topic that's very
nice but that's what the topic was
we weren't comparing goods and bad
stories we were explaining
how and why private investment is not an
either or
in relationship to work or co-ops the
one of the fastest growing industries
in spain is something called the
mondragon cooperative corporation
it's a family of worker co-ops they're
not even worker management
i don't know if this isn't even a good
it is it is it is the seventh largest
corporation in spain
it's a federation of corporations excuse
me it's a federation of corporations and
it's not even worker managed
that's just worker owned and they have
all the same exploitative problems they
go to south america for labor
they rely on contract labor chomsky's
criticized the mondragon thing for
existing in a capitalist framework
forever
and even if this was your go-to killer
example the mondragon federation of
co-ops exists under a capitalist
framework
could i finish or do you need to tell me
about the mondagon corporation
i didn't mean to interrupt your lecture
i'm sorry continue sure you did
come on who you think you're kidding the
mondegun corporation has
many parts the biggest single part of it
are
a collection of worker co-ops if this
were the united states we'd call it a
holding company
which is a collection of subsidiaries
that do a variety of things
it's very common in the united states
and it is very common
in the world of worker co-ops to do that
as well the different
divisions help each other the co-ops
support one another
that's how the mondragon corporation
went from six people in 1956
to over a hundred thousand now most of
the people
in the mondragon corporation function
within
their members about 200 companies
each of which has workers one person one
vote
making democratic decisions this company
has been extraordinarily successful
it has out-competed its capitalist
competitors that's how it became so
large
that's how it becomes so successful as
it has been
it has rules it maximizes because you
raised that before
a variety of objectives it is not
focused
exclusively on profits the notion that
profit
is the bottom line is the very
convenient
economic nonsense because profits go
into the hands
of the capitalists at the top and of
course they want the company to maximize
profits because that's what they get
they don't maximize wages
because that's what they don't get other
people get that
if the other people ran the business its
objectives would not just be
profit but the well-being of those
workers the community's well-being
a whole lot of other objectives
to maximize and you'd have to choose
among them
you wouldn't have the essential profit
maximizing
which we teach in economics without it
explaining to our students
that by maximizing profit the whole
company's life is devoted
to maximizing the return of a very small
number of people
within it okay this is what has changed
in a worker co-op that's why it's so
different
from capitalism it's decisions
investment
growth distribution of income all the
big decisions
would be made with a different set of
objectives
because a different set of people with
different interests
are making those decisions for a society
like ours
that blabbers on about democracy you'd
think this was the most attractive
possible way to proceed because it
democratizes the economy
by democratizing the enterprises at the
core of that
uh economy instead we live in a society
which pretends that you can have
political democracy even though in
economics you have an
autocracy a tiny aristocracy running
each enterprise doing what it wants
maximizing the part of the output
it gets namely the profit and therefore
we get surprised that our political
democracy doesn't work real well
hello that's because it's trying to sit
on top of an
economic system that is the opposite of
democratic
the proposal of socialists is a proposal
to extend democracy from the political
realm
to the economic realm why that is
frightening to people who otherwise say
they favored democracy i find
amazing i find it equally amazing that
throughout this entire monologue
you're all you're advocating for are
liberal markets with a little bit more
government intervention
if you want to talk about mondrag
absolutely if you want to talk about
mondragon we can talk about mondragon
until we're both blue in the face
one it's not worker managed okay it is
just worker owned a lot of the
management that comes
within a lot of the mondragon federation
come from other workers but they do not
vote on all of their policies or
productions that is absolutely not true
number two mondragon does run itself for
profit that's why if you only change the
means of production and not the mode of
production you are still producing
commodities
for a profit now it happens in this case
that the profit is going to the workers
but it still absolutely runs for a
profit
that's why socialists point to it and
say look at how successful it is part of
the reason why successful is the amazing
revenues and profits that it returns to
workers that are generated and then
number three mondragon in order to
continue to grow in order to continue
growing one of the problems that
mondragon has started to face recently
and it's one of the reasons why it's
criticized by
people like chomsky is because it had to
continue to acquire more and more
workers
that do not get controlling shares that
don't have the ability to vote what's
going on mondragon also trades
across markets including going to places
like south america and trading with
exploited workers
so i don't think that mondrag and
finally mondragon exists
under a capitalist mode of economics
like mondragon exists and interacts with
other people within a capitalist economy
which i think is good
if mondragon works and succeeds that's
awesome i think it's cool i like to see
alternative types of businesses succeed
but i don't understand how you can talk
about the successes of mondragon
and then say that like well this is an
example of the failures of capitalism
when mondragon exists and
thrives right now under a capitalist
framework interacting with so many other
capitalist sections of the economy so
many other capitalist countries in the
world
my problem is that by moving more
towards what you want you would use
government policy to necessarily
disallow
the types of private ownership or
private investment that have been so
important with other types of inventions
around the world you can you can keep
saying that i'm making stuff up but at
the end of the day
the problem that we're having to explain
the problem we're having is i
th the definition of socialism and i
notice that this is like the it seems to
be a key problem with people that
call themselves socialists your
definition of socialism is so amorphous
and morphing at any particular point in
time i
still don't really have you seem to be
having trouble with it but that doesn't
make it amorphous
it absolutely is amorphous even your
definition of capitalism is absolutely
amorphous
um where i i hear rules well you're just
not familiar with it i'm absolutely
familiar with it
like i i absolutely am able to if you
would like to ask me for my definition
of any of these things i would be glad
to explain it and you can tell me you
can correct me professor if you think
i'm incorrect in my understanding of
things
but i believe that when i ask you to
tell me like what is capitalism what is
socialism and it feels like i'm i'm
listening to quebec you know read off
the board in jeopardy i feel like that's
damaging to the position that you're
trying to explain more so than me asking
the question
yeah well let me correct you about
mondragon
that which is by the way how it's
pronounced mondragon has
multiple parts some of the parts are the
adjustments it's made to living in a
capitalist world that's absolutely
correct
that would have to be any worker
richard industries that grew up in
feudalism
oh sorry do you mind repeating that last
line you just cut out there for one
second
right any worker co-op
that forms now has to exist within a
framework of a society that's organized
differently that's exactly the way it
was when capitalism emerged
out of feudalism the early capitalist
enterprises
towns villages had to exist within a
feudal
framework they had to come to terms with
that
some of them were able to do it others
of them disappeared or were overthrown
by feudalism until they got big enough
and strong enough and learned from the
mistakes
of early experiments in capitalism how
to set up a system
that would be what it now is the global
system
i expect the socialists to kind of
replicate that experience
russia was an experiment china's a
better one
cuba vietnam and so on they make efforts
they're learning what you do
what you don't do what you replicate
what you avoid
and they will get eventually to the
scale
and sense of how to do it on a more
global scale
that's how feudalism happened that's how
slavery happened that's how capitalism
happened
and it's reasonable to expect that's how
socialism
will happen there is no simple
definition of
socialism that would be to use your
words correct
no agency gives you out a license this
is correct
that one isn't a tradition
as lively as global as socialism
is always going to have different
interpretations
different definitions that argue with
one another
that's healthy that's normal there's
nothing
fuzzy or amorphous about it the idea
that you can have
one definition is an authoritative
authoritative and authoritarian notion
that there isn't debate
and contestation when there always is
my job was to give you three of the
major definitions
of socialism that contest in the world
today that are widely accepted by
everybody of course not
but those are the ones that are around
and it's reasonable
to talk about the tradition in that way
can you undergo let me finish mondragon
is an experiment a very successful one
you can if you like attribute everything
to capitalism that happens that's good
and attribute everything bad that
happens to the absence of capitalism
this is never interesting and that's
really not very interesting and i'm not
going to
you know i'm not going to get into that
i will tell you it's good because
there's some remarkable things
that mondragon has done along the way
the majority of its workers voted
the following rule the best paid person
in mondragon cannot get more than eight
to nine times what the least best paid
person is this
i've been there i've been there i've
watched it
it's just not true so you're telling me
that of all the employees in mondragon
the highest paid employees that was a
decision
that was a decision made by a large
number of the worker co-ops that make
that
so you're telling me that the highest
paid employee in mondragon
it has a ratio of what they're any of
the let me finish in many of the
component
co-ops there you go okay that's correct
it's a holding company of many many
co-ops
in many many of those co-ops i can't
speak for everyone
this was a common rule i went and spoke
with them
i interrogated them about it
and that's what i discovered they passed
a rule after much debate
that a maximum difference of eight to
one you know that corporate ceos in this
country
get roughly on average 300 times what
the lowest paid worker or even the
average worker in their
uh employee class what is the ratio of
what is the ratio they were able to do
something about
inequality wow here they are
successful in growing they're the
seventh biggest corporation
they're the envy of most other
corporations in europe who cannot
show such a history but they were
concerned
not just to maximize profit but to do
something
like limit the inequality that otherwise
is so corrosive
to societies like ours and they were
able to do that
that's an interesting quality thomas
piketty released a book in 2014
in which he demonstrates in 600 pages
that
every single capitalism we have a record
of
has built into it a tendency to ever
greater inequality that is only
periodically interrupted by revolts from
below
like what we had in the 1930s in this
country which
never are durable because once the
revolt passes
the tendency of capitalism to in
inequality
grows that has always been an
inspiration to socialists
to advocate for a system that might have
within it
a built-in mechanism to at least
reduce the inequality that that
haunts capitalism and
the reality is that mondragon and not
only that
have demonstrated that there is a
quality of worker co-ops
that does and effectively a good job
of addressing the inequality that
otherwise
haunts capitalism and that would be an
interesting
way to understand why socialists
would be drawn they are not worker
managed
the way a corporation works is there are
three layers roughly
the employees who do most of the work
the managers who supervise the employees
and then another group of people to whom
we give the name
directors the board of directors
the shareholders elect the board of
directors because they're the ones who
receive
legally the profits and they decide
what is to be produced how it's to be
produced what technology to use
where the production happens and what is
done with the profits
the managers don't do that so to talk
about
gentlemen gentlemen we're coming up to
we're coming up to the hour now um
we have had uh a disproportionate amount
of talking time i think uh by you
professor wolf while at the same time
uh destiny would you want to give a
closing statement to this as we're
coming up
i'll give you a couple minutes to
respond um i mean i just i take issues
the audience
yeah i mean i just i i man there's so
many things
citing i just think it's incredibly
disingenuous to open with mondragon
has 80 000 employees and they voted to
have an eight to one pay between owners
and and their and their not owners the
highest paid employee and the lowest
paid employee
but that's not true you corrected
yourself after i corrected you which i'm
grateful for it's within
within the co-ops within that federation
i'm willing to be that if i were to ask
you you probably couldn't tell me what
the highest paid employee
within the mondragon federation is what
is the ratio of their pay to the lowest
paid employee of the mondragon
federation
because it has an incredible vertical
structure in terms of how it interacts
with itself
now i could just as easily construct to
a world where the ratio of pay
between the ceo of amazon or walmart is
much is
is much smaller where the ratio uh
closes between the lowest paid employee
if i create a walmart or amazon holding
company
and i simply split off all the
managerial people or some sectors of
that company into their own individual
companies
and break it up like that the way that
mondragon has not to say that mondragon
has failed
not to say that they have totally
different sectors they have i'm not
making this stuff up everybody can go
and look at how the company is
structured everybody
can go and look at the different types
of things they have grocery stores
they've got a financial sector
right all right yes but they do not
separate out their managers they do not
separate out one
group of workers with high pay from
others that's a hustle
that would be i agree it would be a
hospital
is just that's make-believe you know you
acknowledge that the
argument is so difficult that you have
to make up the information to support it
my argument is so concrete that i don't
think i've had to bring up feudalism a
single time to make any of my points or
ask you any questions related to any of
your points
um so something something something i'm
curious about
would why wouldn't you consider just
going by the incredibly generous
definition you give me a point one
social
why wouldn't you consider the democratic
party in the united states a socialist
party
as a party that wants to see more uh
more stuff returned to americans wants
to see people with greater control of
the workplace
um had members that were pushing for 20
ownership in the share of companies
bernie sanders aoc why wouldn't you
consider the democratic party in the
united states a socialist party
because it opposes almost everything you
just mentioned it has a small wing
now that is in favor of it who by the
way call themselves
socialists but the establishment of the
democratic party
its history over the last hundred years
since uh franklin
that's not fair why would we why would
you talk about the history of it that is
that's not relevant because that's
because history is always absolutely not
relevant you've
you've said yourself that the history no
you've said yourself that the way that
we look at socialism today is different
than it was 100 years ago
joseph biden is a product of that
history as he himself says
that party has been unable to make a
government
they couldn't even preserve the level of
government intervention
that was achieved in the 1930s the last
70 years have been a rollback
of the new deal an undoing of it
and that was done as much by the
democratic party as the republicans
they the republicans pushed harder the
democrats could not only not
advance on what was achieved in the
1930s
they couldn't even preserve it that's
why we have an unemployment problem now
and have had a terrible experience i
think we have an unemployment
no absolutely not an unemployment
problem
proposed a jobs program of the federal
government
the way worked so well in the 1930s you
couldn't even have the courage to come
up with
with what was already done it's
been a retreat democratic party has been
a retreat from what it did before
all that aoc and and bernie are trying
to do
is to bring back the little bit of
socialism
that the last 75 years of the democratic
party have been devoted
to getting rid of that's why they're so
embarrassed
these political centrists by the rise of
the left
they thought it was over no
this is an unimaginable analysis of
political parties today in the united
states
i don't think the closed shop policies
that bain are advocating for
represent some walk-back and policies or
i don't think that the democratic party
and the republican party push
equally or even remotely similarly for
the types of economies that they'd like
to see today
um whether or not you have problems with
how the democratic party functions i
don't know if your issues are with the
democratic party or the politicians that
americans elect i know that it's a very
popular pastime among lefties to
demonize the democratic party for not
being able to authoritarianly
or totalitarianly rule the country uh
absent you know the other half of
congress it seems like a lot of people
uh
on the left don't seem to understand how
our government functions i don't know if
that includes you or not
um but yeah i think just given
given we have we have folks like you
that will help us
uh yeah i guess we'll see yes
i mean all i learned the thing that i've
learned the most today i'm happy to see
that the democratic party under
definition one of socialism i guess is
considered
uh at least somewhat of a socialist part
of you as they are uh believers of
enterprise and private capitalists and i
guess
yeah i just spoke against that how you
got out of that
well you started to you you started to
you started to appeal
you started to appeal to things the
democratic parties advocated for or
appealed to a history 100 years back
like okay we've turned we've turned into
a fox news channel let's
let's slow it down we're gonna get right
to the audience q a okay
all right so we have uh we have hundreds
and hundreds of questions unfortunately
we're not gonna get to all of them i'm
gonna try and time
uh both of your responses to about two
minutes so i'll give you like a 10 to 15
second warning when you're coming up to
that
um so the first one is going to you
destiny
what could convince you uh that your
system or your defense of capitalism
is wrong and that socialism is a better
path forward
um i think seeing these things try it on
a smaller level and then having more
success on larger and progressively
larger levels would be convincing
um the thing that oftentimes troubles me
when people advocate for different
economic systems is
uh much like wolfe has done and says
maybe the he won't say he's done this
but the moralizing of like the
relationship between an employee and
employer or the moralizing
of different aspects of who owns the
means of production or or who works in
the means of production
i'm not really interested in the
relationship between a boston worker
what i'm more interested in are the
material conditions of people at the end
of the day
um if different relationships are more
beneficial to growing the economy
rather than shrinking the economy but
producing a quote unquote better
relationship
i'm more in favor of the former than the
latter i like capitalism because i think
that
having private enterprise uh adequately
allocates capital into sectors of the
economy they desperately need that
capital allocated to it
um i understand that uh wolfe is
laughing because he's probably gonna say
something like oh well what about
healthcare and education and i'm so glad
that me and the rest of my liberal and
even neoliberal friends agree
that there are times when the government
can step in and it can alleviate some of
the problems that the free market
doesn't address for instance capitalism
doesn't solve well for things like
health care or education
something that we desperately need to
realize in the united states as we work
to
i guess you could say socialize those
industries which i'm so glad can happen
in a capitalist framework
all right uh professor wolf do you want
to respond to any of that or just get a
direct question
and if you are going to respond i'm
going to keep the timing to the
two-minute window no i
no i think this is rehashing stuff we
went over so
how about another question all right so
for
professor wolf were a state to become
socialists how would it thrive within a
hostile capitalist world without
resorting to the authoritarianism
and imperialism of 20th century
socialism
i find this sort of remarkable these
kinds of questions
imperialism the imperialism that we
study
as people who are interested in this
topic
is a product of capitalism the
subordination of the third world
asia africa and latin america was a
subordination
organized and operated by capitalist
institutions and capitalistically
dominated societies
imperialism serious issue for sure
but it is serious issue that is the
product
and the activity of capitalism
if you would like to talk about things
the soviet union did
and china has done in terms of their
activities
in and around other countries and you
want to apply
the term imperialism
fine you'd have to make some adjustments
because the logic was different
and the outcomes were different and the
scale of it was
utterly different we didn't have the
soviets and the chinese at least not yet
have had not organized world wars to
hold on and to expand
their imperialist empires like world
wars one and two
so it i find the whole question strange
to put forward especially without any uh
explanation
and now to address briefly the question
what a state that became socialist
would do depends on which of the three
basic definitions i offered that state
embraced if it believed that socialism
was what you have in western europe and
scandinavia
that's what it would do it would have no
problem
excuse me oh we got 15 seconds left okay
that's what it would do if it followed
the soviet model that's what it would do
and if it did the kind of thing that i'm
advocating and the socialists like me do
then it would be devoted to changing the
organization of enterprises
democracy
into enterprise inside capitalist
enterprises
okay to destiny do you think that jeff
bezos works hundreds of thousands of
times harder than his workers
why should he be the richest person in
the world um you don't get compensated
based on how hard you work you get
compensated based on the demand for your
particular set of skills
um there's probably less people that can
work in the position that bezos does and
there are people that can work
in any other more entry level position
at amazon
wow okay wait wait do you disagree with
that do you think just as many people
could handle being the ceo of a
multi-billion dollar company as could
handle being somebody that
works in a grocery store or a fast food
restaurant is there a simple yes or no
to that or am i about to get another
lecture
well you don't want an answer you you
want you just want the answer you want
you don't want it in a
form can i get an answer that doesn't
involve feudalism
that's not cute is that what the point
is here
okay
why don't you just let me respond
without coaching me how to do it
can we do that okay i'll give i'll give
i'll give you two minutes i'll go back
we'll go there
fine the the idea
advanced by you earlier
that you don't have one person walk away
with 200 billion dollars roughly the
estimate of businesses worth and the
vast majority of his employees
unable to pay for their kids to go to
college is a distribution
of the profits of that business that
is morally reprehensible
that's how the wealth was accumulated by
the distributions
of share dividends to shares share
expansion and share improvement in value
we have a system that rewards one
person with 200 billion and another one
with thirty thousand dollars
that's a remarkable decision to make in
a community that
calls itself uh democratic or that what
likes to believe
it wants to give people a fair and equal
chance no fairness here no equality
it is revolting to me that anyone
could find this reasonable and to
explain it by saying
there's a demand that's simply what the
corporations
give each other the demand they're the
ones who
create the which they then
fill with themselves because they're the
ones who hire
each other for that job it's a
remarkable
self-serving system where the folks at
the top
give themselves as much as they can
get away with and if it were looked at
that that way
it would not survive 10 minutes wait
what was the original question
wait hold on we were asking we were
asking how we react to that inequality
no the question was why i asked you why
do you think bezos is compensated so
much more than a love like a frontline
employee do you think that
the demand for those talents is equal
between somebody that could be a ceo
versus somebody that could work in a
sense i don't think the demand
for that talent is an explanation of
anything you'd have to explain why the
demand is what it is
who makes the demand sure i can yeah
what we can talk about all of that i
would imagine you as a professor should
know the answer to all these questions
right
who make who where is the demand to
running a multi-billion dollar company
that turns profits for people that i
mean like you can explain all of these
things i don't know why you would
pretend there's not answers you're very
clear
you can you can cast whatever persians
you want on my
qualification i'm not casting any
inspirations on your qualifications
it's disappointing that instead of
getting an actual answer to anything it
was all moralized that's all
we had but okay let's let's see the q a
okay sure
um all right the next the next question
uh i believe goes to
you destiny if you identify as a sock
dem
why is it that you did not publicly
support bernie sanders during his run
um i think that some of what bernie
sanders advocates for
goes in directions that i think would be
detrimental to the economy there were
larger policies that he had i don't know
how i feel necessarily about a national
jobs guarantee i definitely don't like
the push for like nationwide rent
control
um these are just uh certain types of i
don't know the economy can handle like a
15 an hour federal minimum wage
at the at the federal level um there
were just a lot of policies that bernie
sanders pushed for i think at one point
he pushed also for that plan
for twenty percent of every business
would be owned by workers i don't know
how the united states managed that
and then his version of medicare for all
went like more extreme than any other
version of socialized healthcare in the
world
um a lot of these things just pushed it
way too far for me i didn't think they
were politically viable
i would have taken bernie sanders easily
over donald trump or probably a few of
the other democratic candidates but
i just felt like they were better better
middle grounds than what bernie sanders
was pushing for
okay to you professor wolf um what is
the best way to judge
the success of an economic system uh
such as capitalism or socialism
well you know there are many many
dimensions many standards many metrics
that you can use
one of them is economic growth the other
one is the distribution of wealth and
income that the society
and the economic system generate
for me i i'm committed to asking the
question whether the people who do the
work who pour their brains and
their muscles into the production of
goods and services
are or are not entitled to participate
in deciding
how those goods and services are
distributed how the income
if they're sold in markets is
distributed i would like to see human
beings have the right
to participate democratically in the
workplace it is at least as important
as participating democratically in the
residential community
where you live we have the forms in the
latter
and the complete absence of it so for me
a test of an economic system would be
how much
real democratic participation in both
work and residential community life
people are able to have and on that
ground
capitalism falls so far short that it's
an easy choice
okay to destiny uh under the current
conditions of covid and everything
that's happened as
so many people seem to be suffering and
a distratified people between classes
how can you still defend capitalism
i i don't know people seem to i believe
sorry this one is specifically about the
u.s response i think that
yeah sure people like to attribute like
so many strange ills i i noticed um
professor did it earlier when he said
our unemployment is very high right now
like that's a fault of capitalism and
we're just ignoring the worldwide
pandemic that's currently occurring
um i i just there are ways that our
government right now
can respond to the pandemic that don't
require it to be a socialist government
there have been far more left-leaning
governments and other countries that
have failed to respond to the pandemic
you can look across the entirety of
europe for examples of that if you wish
um i just i think that these two things
are totally disassociated from other i
think that it is possible to maintain a
capitalist economy
while also having adequate intervention
from the government to alleviate the
problems that we have with the pandemic
which
we're starting to see under biden
unfortunately it's taken a while but
even under trump we saw things like the
character and whatnot as well
wait wait let him keep speaking he still
has uh oh no sorry i didn't want to
interrupt him during my answer go ahead
professor
yeah i would respond in in two ways
number one
the united states has four percent of
the world's population
and 20 of the world's covet deaths
for a rich country with a well-developed
medical system
that is a systemic failure beyond
all words so for me yeah
this is a problem of a system that could
not prepare itself
properly for a pandemic it knows could
happen
given the one that we had a century ago
and there are many since that time
and it is likewise a system that was not
able to cope
very well with what it was unprepared
for the second and final thing i will
say
is i notice that there are three
governments in the world right now
the united states brazil and india
characterized by right-wing governments
for most of the time of the pandemic
trump here bolsonaro in brazil and modi
in
india their performances these three
countries
of these three right wing super pro
capitalist leaders
are among the worst in the world
more than pretty much every place else
and i think that speaks volumes to
what's at stake
in making this decision between the
pro-capitalist
and the pro-socialists i mean just to be
clear the uk
italy i mean like there are other
countries that did worse in the united
states and then
comparably there are countries that also
did um that's an amazing standard to you
wait wait wait wait wait wait wait wait
let's finish it
wait just let this knee finish with this
response we'll do it one minute time and
then we'll we can get a response back i
mean like if you want to look at like
the deaths per 1 million population like
a lot of countries around the world drop
the ball on this some did very well
and some of the ones that did very well
are capitalist countries you know places
like south korea that have like heavily
liberalized their economy or bastions of
like capital success have done very very
well when it comes to tracking and
dealing with this
um you know australia new zealand are
capitalist countries and they also did
very well countering this
um places like the united kingdom that
has socialized healthcare that provides
education for its citizens they had a
worth
worse deaths per million than the united
states did um
again i'm not saying that like hooray
capitalism can save us or you know any
of that stuff i'm just saying that how
your country did
i don't think is necessarily reliant on
the uh organization that you have
in your economy i think it's more
important to see what type of action
does your government take
which i don't know maybe wolf has a
definition of socialism where it's
also the government coming in and
intervening for diseases but you know
whether you have all worker co-ops or
all privately uh managed firms i don't
see how that matters when it comes to
how your country addresses
uh coronavirus
[Music]
do you want a one minute response to
that and then we'll move on to the next
question yes okay
at the beginning of this discussion
steve
rattled off about how
socialist societies have never succeeded
so
he generally equated the socialism but
the success
i try to do that now in terms of the
coveted response
and he takes exception he doesn't want
it to be so
he doesn't like the linking of the
social system
with the problem well you really can't
have it both ways
i didn't point out that socialism come
in capitalist countries
had some general difference i pointed
out that the
three of the worst examples of mass
death
happened in societies led by people on
the extreme
right that that leaves a big open space
for the variety of
other less extreme situations
that's the point of it all it's not that
capitalism is the cause of everything
but that it contributes in ways that you
can identify
and trace i i i i
can i get a five
i think that you would have an easier
time blaming chernobyl on socialism than
you would the coronavirus response on
capitalism that's all i'm saying
exactly that's exactly what you're
saying i see that thank you
okay uh can we uh two more questions
gentlemen uh do we have time for that is
that all right i got all the time in the
world
okay uh to professor wolf worker
cooperators survive and thrive all over
the world by the thousands
why couldn't we build a stable
sustainable economy based on the bottom
up democratically when cooperatives
emulate that model here in the u.s why
hasn't it taken it off yet or sorry why
hasn't it taken off yet
well there are many reasons you know
capitalism and i will apologize in
advance for
referring to feudalism and other systems
they not only take a long time to get
going and to settle in
but when they do one of the reasons they
succeed is that they develop
a culture a politics that is consistent
with
that is built so it reinforces the
economic system
upon which it sits capitalism is no
different
if you begin to break down as capitalism
is now doing and you see efforts
whether they work at co-ops socialist
movements uh
labor movements and so on beginning the
construction the slow
construction of alternatives they're
going to encounter
politics and culture that stand in the
way
politics and culture that militate
against it
i can't tell you the number of times i
explain worker co-ops to people
who really can't get their heads at
first around well gee how do they get
money or
how do they solve their problems or how
do they grow
because in their world there has to be a
boss
and the boss has to be in other words
they have adjusted their own life
expectations and understanding of how
the world works
to the way it is now all of that is
breaking down but it takes
time and i think that's why the you'll
see
that while worker co-ops have existed
from the beginning when the united
states was even just a colony
why it takes a long time before the
combination of breakdown of capitalism
and the emergence of these alternatives
gets up to speed so that people's
political and cultural
awarenesses allow them to flourish
all right final question to you destiny
uh why do you never mention vietnam
especially in relationship to
how they handled kovid and their success
in that area
um i don't know specifically why i
looked into um for all of my cover
debates it was usually
new zealand australia south korea
and then on the flip side places like
the united states and the the uk for
examples of successfully handling the
pandemic
versus unsuccessfully handling it um in
terms of uh that that's for the
coronavirus stuff in terms of like
economic history
my understanding is that vietnam tried
the you know their
single party state labor unions kind of
like this under one party they had a
heavily socialized economy
but much like what existed in the ussr
people after their you know work shifts
would have to spend time throughout the
day um engaging with like a shadow
economy or kind of a black economy or a
black market where they would have to
buy and sell the goods that weren't
otherwise
available in their country um in the in
russia they did this with a system or in
the ussr they did this with a system of
blots
um i don't know if they've got a formal
name for it and the vietnamese economy
but it seems like the way that vietnam
has worked to kind of modernize their
economy through i think they're called
the i'm going to butcher that
uh pronunciations like the doi moy
reforms um through all of these
referendums they did in terms of
bringing their economy more in line with
being more successful
these have all involved the
liberalization of their economy the
association with other economies around
the world
and you could even see with some
multilateral trade agreements like the
tpp
outside pressure was actually forcing
vietnam to modernize on some of its
labor rights the socialist party of that
country was not able to do it on its own
it needed some external association
and we can see that within countries
even socialist countries that they still
have massive problems with some of their
populations i mean we can point to the
weaker situation that exists in china as
an example of what is supposedly a
socialist
country having a huge problem dealing
with uh you know uh
equitable shares of how to treat people
within its own borders
all right final question to you uh
professor wolf
uh under your system of worker
cooperatives would i still get my
playstation 5
absolutely you'd have to struggle a
little bit for it you'd have to talk to
your fellow workers you'd have to talk
about the distribution of income
you'd have to compare your desire for
playstation
uh against all the other interests of
all the other people
it wouldn't be something you worked out
on your own with your particular boss
in any way would have to be a democratic
decision you'd have to come to terms
with that the way you do with democratic
decisions
now in our society to the extent uh
that we have them uh and i would like to
add only that
if if steve is interested he could also
look at the experience with covid
uh that the cubans had because it is in
many ways even
better than the ones that the vietnamese
had
uh for the purposes of complete
transparency i'm just going to state
that that last question was actually my
own
and now i will move on to closing
statements uh we'll begin
uh with uh destiny and then we will end
with richard wolff
uh you have three minutes oh geez i
didn't write a closing statement um
so at the end of this i guess my
important takeaway for all of this is i
think that it is crucial
not to moralize our economic systems i
think that when you start to moralize
economic systems what you forget
is that an economic system is merely a
tool um i don't want to ask a question
of like is a hammer good or evil i want
to ask you know like
what is the best type of nail that you
can hit with a particular hammer when
you begin to point out whether or not a
particular economic system is in and of
itself
good or evil then you lose sight of what
economies are supposed to do which is
efficiently allocate capital or natural
resources in ways that make a country as
prosperous as possible
i do agree with richard wolff and
probably with every socialist or every
left-leaning person around the world
that there are a ton of problems that
exist in the western world and we're
specifically in the united states today
relating to things like inequality
social justice
a lack of access to things like health
care or education or
basic things like food stamps or shelter
or um
or other like basic necessities i just
don't see how a socialist society solves
literally any of these things
and i don't feel like i've ever been
given an adequate explanation by any
socialist
for how they would organize their
society usually these arguments are
incredibly amorphous or vague such that
literally everything is socialism like
you can still have private enterprise
and co-ops and the government does some
things and voila that's socialism
which just sounds like liberalism to me
with government intervention which is
liberalism
or they try to make arguments for more
strict forms of socialism
but i think that it's hard to get them
to admit that in those stricter forms of
socialism they would disallow things
like private investment
and i guess it bothers me because so
many innovations and things have existed
only under the framework of capitalism
that
even with public research and public
pushing you weren't able to get for
instance i believe the led was
discovered
um or was invented in russia like 100
years ago
and it wasn't until western private
enterprise took a hold of that invention
and started utilizing it then anybody
was able to actually enjoy the invention
all right thank you and now professor
wolf closing statements your three
minutes
sure i think it's very hard for people
to
break out of the straitjacket that
capitalism having existed for 300 years
imposes on us often unconsciously
often through the medium of our parents
our teachers
and so forth uh i respect that that's
difficult human beings have a hard time
doing that
i'm included but i think that what is
unique here is that all those
problems of american capitalism that
steve just listed
the difference is whether you see those
as distinct problems
that you as a good liberal think that
the government could address
or that some institutional adjustment
could address
people who have looked at the
inequalities the instability the
injustices of capitalism
have tried that for a long time and it
doesn't
work the fact of the matter is we have
more inequality now
than we had 10 40 and 60 years ago
that's the system that we live in it's
as though what the liberal
does is look for every possible
explanation
other than that the basic system is the
problem
and system change is the solution
and one last effort to clarify since it
seems murky
for steve the difference
i advocate is a radical transformation
of the workplace so that the person who
comes to work is no longer
overwhelmingly an employee a drone
told where to sit and what to do with
what machine on what occasion
and then at the end of the day is told
go home what happens to what you helped
to produce
is none of your business that
transforming that
into a collective community that
democratically decides
so that every worker has two job
descriptions
the particular task and your equal
participation
in running designing and organizing the
enterprise
that is a liberation of human capability
it is a transformation
of life from the bottom up and
represents a kind of socialism
which were it to be achieved would be a
control on the government
so it does what the people need and not
get shifted off to other things that
sustain
the state as against the people that's a
lesson
learned from the earlier socialisms that
the newer socialisms
have incorporated the mass of people
will determine
as capitalism especially in the united
states declines
whether when and how to move
forward but the yearning to do better
than we're doing in u.s capitalism
that's already a fact it's now only a
question
where it'll go the very fact that this
conversation is happening
and that someone like me was invited to
participate
is itself a sign of where things are
going
all right thank you so much for
participating in this on both parts
uh would either of you like to plug any
of your current social projects
or what you have going on
um i'm good okay richard
all i would say if anyone is interested
in the kinds of things i have to say
we maintain a website democracy at work
dot info from there you can find
everything that we do
very simple all right thank you so much
thanks everybody
i don't know what to do so i ran into a
similar problem with pogon because
i think that wolf is like relatively
polite
um so i don't want to like cut him off
but like
god damn when he just like
so how do you feel about amazon well you
see
in 1823 when feudalism was a big part of
the catholic church it's like
oh my god stop why are we doing this
how do we define when we talk about what
a what a dog is
we start off by saying that it's not a
cat wait what
there were so many things where i wanted
to i i think i got a little bit more
aggressive towards the end
i was trying to be like more gentle in
the beginning but then it felt like he
was getting like fairly condescending
but i don't want to like i don't want to
cut him off because i don't know if um
i don't know if that's like rude or not
um but then
it felt like yeah i don't know i so i
started to take a few more shots towards
the last half
but i hope i established that it was
because he was kind of starting it i
don't know
um he got super mad right after your
initial statement yeah like right after
my opening he's like uh
socialism is i hate to admit this
i hope my mom's not in chat the the
conservatives were right i guess
socialism to people is just when the
government does stuff i guess
that was definition one um
i didn't get to get to like any of my
five challenges
what level of violence is acceptable for
you to reach a social estate
how do we decide which businesses are
allowed to exist in a socialist society
but it felt like he squirmed around a
lot of these so like when i asked him
because i asked him like so are you
saying that like only
um like only co-ops can exist in the
studies well no but i'd like more co-ops
than private firms because well how do
you enforce that
um oh and another thing that i hit on i
might this might be exclusively how i
debate lefties in the future
um i think i'm just going to talk about
capital markets because i feel like a
lot of people in the left just don't
know anything about the stock market
which is a little bit surprising to me
because if you're going to talk about or
critique capitalism
i feel like private equity markets or
like financial markets or capital
markets i feel like that's really
important to understand
it's like when you say things like well
you know a corporation has no obligation
to return the money to you like wait
what do you mean
why do you think they started paying
ceos in stock
instead of in actual cash we the whole
point of this is because they want
um the quote unquote owners of the
company to be maximizing returns for
shareholders like
i i think i think that i really do feel
like in the future
i think for lefties i think i'm just
going to exclusively say hey let's talk
about the stock market
um most socialists don't understand
materials conditions yeah i just
geez
i felt that he was floundering in terms
of investors yeah and then and then when
he was like well i can point to hundreds
of thousands of examples that doesn't
happen oh yeah i'm sure
i mean look at enron like of course
there are going to be situations where
people [ __ ] each other over yeah of
course
the majority of c-level employees
six-figure bonuses are all locked into
stock for years yeah of course
i think your complaining about feudalism
was bad having a long historical
perspective on different ways of
organizing society seems proper and
relevant
when talking about the possible
evolution from one economic one complex
economics
well so technically oh god i hate to do
this okay
i hate to i hate to debate bro you here
but i'm gonna use one debate bro term
okay
it is fallacious to say that because we
came from one system and we're going
somewhere else
necessarily means we're going to go from
this system to the next and
even if i did grant that causality even
even if i did say because here is the
argument he's making
we went from a to b and then from b to c
and then from c to d
now we're definitely gonna go from d to
e even if i did grant that dde is going
to happen
there's no conclusion there's no reason
to believe that e is socialism
e could just as easily be a fascist
state e could just as easily be a
post-nuclear war a post-apocalyptic
anarcho capitalist anarcho communist
anarcho syndactylus whatever
society right he could be anything right
so that that
whole line of of speaking is hey
i try to avoid debate bro terms and
right but it's fallacious it doesn't
make any sense
um it is a non-sequitur it doesn't
logically follow that because we went
from a to b b to c c to d
therefore we are definitely going to go
from d to e that needs to be
demonstrated
and what e is e could be socialism or
any number
on the any other number of systems that
also needs to be demonstrated that
argument in and of itself is not
compelling sorry [ __ ]
i didn't even get to i didn't get to
address that but um
yeah why did you say history
isn't relevant because i didn't like the
fact that when he was condemning the
actions of the democratic party he
wanted to reach back over a hundred
years and talk about their failures but
when i was trying to get him to tell me
what he believed a socialist country was
or what socialism was
he was like well hold on i'm not going
by marx's definition things are
different now
well hold on if things are going to be
different now for how you define
socialism which by the way that's fair
if you want to use the international
definition now that's fine but you can't
hold the democratic party to account for
things that another democratic party did
100 years ago i don't think that's fair
i don't think you can do that
you have to be consistent in this if you
want to talk about how things are as
they are now that's fine
but if you're if you're um if your
definition of social is going to be so
wide to include private and this is
another thing that bothered me but
i feel like he never actually gave me a
definition of capitalism either
my definition of capitalism or what i
understand capitalism to be
capitalism is when you have private
enterprise meaning you've got people
that can
own companies that don't necessarily
work them and then they interact with
some free market or open market system
that's what
that's how capitalism is it means that i
can go out and buy a business hire other
people to work it and then i can buy and
sell goods on an open market
like that's it that's all that's what
capitalism is but it feels like um
it feels like he wants to like load
things like
capitalism is when the slave and the
master when you have the employee and
the player and the ownership and the
extraction of limits like damn just
let's just like let's just go by
basically so we know what the [ __ ] we're
talking about because
and then his idea of like well i'm not
going to tell you what capitalism is the
way that we work on definitions is by
saying what they're not
and it's like wait what i thought my
jeopardy equip was good do you think it
was good
i'm trying not to i try to do as many
quips but man it felt like he was
getting really angry so i wanted to
i had to start quipping i had to start
equipping he was quipping on me
um yeah [ __ ] i don't know
i you lazyballed that bezos answer you
answered that much better in the past
well i asked the question again he
didn't even
he didn't even remember the question i
hope that stuck with the audience
i don't know if the audience is keeping
track of things as well as i am mentally
i tried to restate it but i asked him
the bezos question and then he talked
for two minutes and i asked him what the
question was and he didn't even remember
and then i had to ask him again and then
he moralized it
he's like wow like jesus
destiny the difference is ontologically
prior to identity but wolf was still
being a dodging dumb [ __ ] okay sure but
we're not having debates on ontology
here okay
i believe that when most people ask like
hey dude
what's that like oh that
well it's not a wall it's not the color
blue um it's not a light
uh it's not an economy it's not like
wait hold on wait we just
tell me what you think this thing what
do you mean like
if we were having like categorical like
discussions or or
or talking about like the nature of
something we were having an ontological
debate
we could do that but that was not the
level of discourse we were at here
that's not what we were talking about
you need to add like 10 more nebraska
steve i tried to get more snarky towards
the end because it felt like
yeah [ __ ] i don't know i feel like this
is going to sound really weird
but i feel like having an unmoderated
in-person debate with him would be a lot
of fun
is he from new york the way that he
talks strikes me as somebody from the
east coast and i i think those
i like people like that because he seems
like he seems like he would be more
combative which would be a lot of fun i
think
um but um yeah [ __ ]
oh massachusetts okay yeah close enough
also destiny why is it wrong in your
opinion to moralize an economic system
sure
so the reason why it's bad to moralize
an economic system
is because people pretend like what we
want exists in the economic system
but that's not true what we want comes
after the economic system
we don't care about what happens within
an economy what we care about is at the
end what the distribution of goods and
services are
so here's an example of this let's say
that we have an economy where the worker
and the owner can only earn two times as
much as each other and everything is
equitably split out and blah blah blah
blah and let's say that society is poor
and starving
would we prefer that or would we prefer
a society with massive inequality where
the poorest people you know can eat
steak dinners every night it's like
right
well okay well obviously we prefer the
latter rather than the former and the
reason why is because we're not really
we shouldn't be moralizing the
relationships that exist within an
economic system we should be looking at
the outcomes that they produce after
economic systems are just tools
that are supposed to be wielded by
policy makers in order to ensure a more
fair distribution at the end of the day
now that being said it might be the case
it might be the case that a socialist
form of organization achieves more
equitable outcomes
however if that is the case we should be
arguing about the outcomes produced by
that system
not the inherent relationships within
that system right
um do you have a preference between a
profitable system with or without any
quality
if you had two separate systems and they
produced the exact same amount of wealth
at the end of the day
then getting one system that is more
equitable within that system would
probably be better it would make things
easier for policy makers right
the content of the relationship implies
something about the outcome missing the
point
no you're wrong you're just wrong i'm
sorry but you're just wrong
isn't half the point of socialism to
actually um create something ethical
inside the system i
removing alienation of workers and such
alienation of workers and all of that
can be achieved within socialism and can
be achieved within capitalism it depends
you can feel alienated in a labor union
you could feel alienated in a private
place to work
there are probably some people that feel
like they have more control over their
job when they work for places like
amazon or facebook where you're given
some degree of freedom or flexibility
over the projects you choose to work on
then there are some people that work
inside labor unions that constantly vote
against what they personally would want
i mean like we can imagine these types
of conditions existing everywhere we can
also imagine we don't have to imagine if
we want to talk historical examples we
can go back to like the 50s and 60s we
can look where labor unions will vote to
disenfranchise minority swathes of their
membership
it took the federal government and the
civil rights age coming in and actually
enforcing externally onto labor unions
worker-controlled unions
um things like equal rights or things
like civil rights because a lot of the
white majority owning people in those
unions the the runners of that union
even with the votes of the minority
black people still weren't able to
achieve equitable conditions for those
black workers
again i'm not blaming the union or the
system capitalism can reinforce racism
uh socialism can reinforce racism
capitalism can also do things reinforce
anti-racism and socialism could
reinforce anti-racism
right now in our society there seems to
be in the past
50 years ago it seems to be the case
that there was a price tag for being
somewhat bigoted for being somewhat
racist
if you made movies or film or if you had
businesses that didn't serve black
people
that didn't showcase uh gay
relationships et cetera et cetera there
was a reward for that in the economy
you're rewarded for being racist you
were rewarded for being homophobic you
were rewarded for being bigoted
nowadays in society it seems as though
that's somewhat flipped now the rewards
exist for being
you know more woke the worker you are as
a company the more you advertise that
sometimes the more money you can make
doing so if you make a hollywood film
today that has more black people more
women you widen your audience right you
widen your markets here look at how
popular like the black panther was
nobody saw that movie earning i think it
grossed over a billion dollars right
um now i'm not saying now to be clear
again
i'm not saying like look capitalism
solved racism all i'm trying to bring
all i wanna
if i can bring anybody on board with
anything at the end of the day
okay if i could bring anybody on board
with anything in the day here is all i
want you to do just stop
thinking of tools as being moral or
immoral
okay there's no reason to assume that by
adding a small amount of your labor to
some capital that you now own that
capital
any more than the capital adding his cap
now the capital is adding his capital
labor owns your labor
right these relationships aren't
inherently moral or immoral we should be
concerned about the material conditions
that exist at the end of the day
okay economies or economic organizations
or economic policies
should only be policies that are wielded
as tools by policymakers
we shouldn't look at these relationships
as inherently moral or immoral we need
to look at the outcomes that these
systems produce
that's all that's all i want to bring
you on board with and if you still think
that like well i think socialism makes
better outcomes than capitalism
okay fine we can argue about that sure
and in some limited cases
you know you might be right or maybe
even a wider case you might be right you
know maybe you can point to
the idea that people getting to vote um
you know when some companies you know
feel you know better about the way that
things run you know my
fiancee's dad in sweden um he lives in
like a uh like a co-op
is like the type of apartment he lives
in my understanding is that those are
pretty popular in sweden
where you move into a building and you
buy a share in that building and then
you live in it you get to vote on like
the changes that happen in that building
and apparently
a lot of people in sweden that really
like that organization you know um you
know and that type of co-op where you
actually control where you live you know
maybe having voting power there is
important maybe i need to choose that
right
all i'm saying is that just don't look
at like these economic tools
which are just tools don't look at them
it's inherently morally immoral because
what happens is
is when it warps your [ __ ] brain it
leads you to saying some things that are
actually
create bad outcomes like something that
you might consider
like a more inherently moral
relationship might get you to a worse
outcome which is something we don't want
right um for instance if we give workers
so like here's
i can give you a hypothetical railroad
example if we give workers autonomy over
their workplace it might be the case
that workers that work in a fossil fuel
industry
will massively vote to overproduce
fossil fuels they might massively
promote
to increase production because they're
protecting their own industry they're
protecting their own jobs
now before somebody says oh well nobody
would ever do that you can look in
places like california
where there are labor unions that
constantly fight against the turning on
of massive solar arrays here because you
know they don't want their jobs to be
threatened you can look at places you
can look at a federation of unions the
largest one in the united states the
afl-cio
you know has a position against the
green new deal because they don't
believe that the green new deal
adequately takes into concerns
uh or takes into its concern the concern
of the workers that exist within their
unions you know
just don't moralize just don't moralize
your economic system it just leads you
to um
it just it poisons your brain it gives
you it it clouds your judgment and it
gives you an inability to
analyze these problems and give you good
prescriptions is my problem
why didn't you open with this moralizing
argument um i tried to but
the problem is that like any time i
asked him any question about anything it
felt like um
i don't i don't feel like my debate
would poke it it felt like he didn't
make like he'd
never wanted to make like a concrete
point or argument it's hard for me to
tell i try to be generous to my
people that i my interlocutors i try to
be generous and say maybe i'm not
understanding something
um maybe i'm just missing something
but i feel like i'm reasonably
intelligent and i feel like i have a
decent grasp of these topics if it feels
like you're dancing around in circles
and it takes you so long to answer any
question
like if i just ask questions like what
is capitalism to you you're like what is
socialism like can you give me and you
have to talk for three minutes and it's
like a 200 year long answer like i don't
know it feels to me like
it feels like a bit of obfuscation is
occurring or rather
like if i i don't want to go the bad
faith route but maybe they do this
unintentionally
what it feels like this is what it feels
like to me it feels like you're scared
of giving me
a concrete definition because you know
that any definition that you give is
going to be inadequate and that you can
be attacked on it
um maybe and maybe i should be maybe i
need to find a way to put me on the
defense more on my things
because the frustrating is if you would
ask me to define anything i tried this
at one point of the debate but then
wolfe ran from it
um it was over the bezos thing i can
tell you exactly why a ceo gets paid
what they do and i can tell you exactly
why
any worker gets paid what they do right
we can talk about like
the marginal cost that the next unit for
the marginal cost of labor going into
the next unit the marginal cost of a
product or we can talk about
supply and demand of different types of
talents in the workplace i can give you
exact answers i don't have to
i don't have to talk for about 200 years
ago you know somebody said this and
that's why i
can give you exactness all of these i
feel like you should be able to do the
same for for any explanation that you're
giving you know
the three card game he played with the
three definitions of socialism was
amazing he claimed that portugal was
socialist so socialism works but he
advocated for the third form not the
first
yeah it reminds me of when unlearning
economics was saying like
oh well 15 an hour minimum wage can be
good here's all these studies that say
twelve dollar minimum age just
minimum wage is possible it's like okay
uh
could you elaborate on why you didn't
consider vietnam's response to covid
um i because i've heard varying things
about like the southeast asian region in
terms of like whether or not they under
report like
because i've heard people claim that
china underreported the amount of
sickness i haven't heard that claim
regarding to vietnam
but i just haven't looked into it enough
and i have other very concrete countries
where i trust the data that comes out of
them
and the three that i typically look at
are south korea and new zealand
australia for like how effective are
lockdowns um and then i'm kind of
familiar with like how western countries
dealt with things um
roughly mainly like the uk and the
united states but i just haven't looked
into vietnam that much in terms of the
i coronavirus like you're saying things
like you may be misunderstanding made
you look bad did i say that a lot during
the debate i tried to cut that
down um because i said that a lot during
pogam i try that to be um
generous to my opponent but i think
rhetorically i don't think it plays well
i tried not to do that as much as i like
oh maybe i don't understand it no i
think i did say it a couple times
yeah i should just i should just not say
that ever because it's
because [ __ ] i feel like i'm i'm trying
to be humble i'm trying to show some
respect
but i really shouldn't uh august pointed
this out what i should be saying instead
of like i don't really understand
what you mean this year you what i
should be saying is you haven't
adequately demonstrated this can you
explain this again that's what i should
be doing
um because that's actually true yeah
i wonder if opening within all socialist
countries have failed put some on the
back foot right again i feel like i have
that several times in my opening
statement but
in the past you've said clearly that
stocks are gambling yet you seem to
define it as specifically receiving ri
you're betting a lot of money on an
individual stock is gambling of course
but that is not at all even remotely
related to anything i've said in this
conversation so i don't know why
also like [ __ ] i dude i should focus on
capital markets
um i see this idiot uh matt cletch or
whatever i see this dumb [ __ ] tweeting
too
um jeff bezos is worth 200 billion
because of his skills well okay
well let's say that instead of jeff
bezos being worth money let's say that
we distribute all of that in stock to
the employees
well what are the employees going to do
with it right they're probably going to
sell the stock
so let's say that the employees sell the
stock to earn some money now instead of
conversation well well now you have a
bunch of employees that work for amazon
that don't own any
stock like you can't get food with stock
let's follow that to its logical
conclusion like what would that even
mean like how would you even like
i don't know or i get well
actually there are answers to this i
don't want to give them though because i
don't think lefties understand capital
markets enough to know what the answers
would be um
rage poke there we can think we could
probably invent some stock schemes to
make it work
so like you would distribute stock and
then you would do a stock split maybe
every two weeks
and then the stock split would be a way
of employees getting paid out and then
you would like combine this with
buybacks strategically in order to
they're like we could probably think of
like complicated stock schemes
in order to do this but like why if you
really want to do this like an employee
could just buy stock with their wage
right like yeah
but i but yeah i don't know [ __ ]
we need to talk about capital markets
way more with lefties because i truly
believe that um
i truly believe that they just don't
understand
anything about capital markets
is there a real reason why bezos having
that much money is bad
um well so to be i know you put money in
quotes him having the money isn't bad or
him having ownership in the company
isn't bad the bad
thing is the unequitable distribution
well no not even really what kind of the
unequitable distribution of wealth of
society
the bad thing is that we have some
people in society that have an immense
amount of wealth
and then we have some people in society
that are immensely [ __ ] if you want to
see things like this play out in the
real world
like go to san francisco it's one of the
most mind-blowing places in the world
you can walk down the street from
businesses
that are worth hundreds of millions of
dollars and see poor people like begging
for food outside of a starbucks
something is like
terminally broken in that system
something is severely [ __ ] there
so when you have some people that seem
to have amassed so much wealth that they
couldn't spend it over the course of a
hundred lifetimes
and then you have other people that are
homeless well it seems like we have a
problem that we have an equity
problem there but hey i mean like these
problems have existed socialist regimes
too you know
soviet soldiers uh soldiers soviet
soldiers
shot ukrainians that were running away
trying to find food so they didn't have
to eat their [ __ ] family members
during the
of demore um china right now is has over
800 000 uyghurs in detention camps
trying to culturally genocide them
um you know vietnam has had its share of
problems under a single-party system
like a ton of like
socialist countries have problems too
and the imperialist thing was so stupid
as well the ussr was an incredibly
imperialist regime
cuba venezuela bolivia like all of these
like socialist countries have also had i
don't know if i'd say balloon but all
these countries have had like severe or
known yeah
have had like severe imperialist things
going on as well like the idea that
imperialism is somehow unique to
capitalists or unique to western
countries
or even a unique like countries have
been imperialists throughout all of
human history like tons of people have
invaded people for natural resources and
et cetera et cetera et cetera and even
mondragon you know relies on contract
labor from south america and from africa
again people have criticized mandarin
for relying on this
one quip that i thought of um that i
didn't say because i feel like it would
have been way too pointed was
when uh when wolf said that world war ii
started because of capitalist powers
what i wanted to chime in there and say
well at least you're consistent about
not wanting the u.s to come in and stop
genocides but i felt like that would
have been
way too i feel like that would have been
way too aggressive so i
held that one back
this is the problem disentangle the
politics from the economics of
capitalism people conflate the two
and he corrected me on this on the
pronunciation of mondragon
yeah and then i i don't know i don't
know if it counted as a rhetorical win
but when
because i got him to say like when a
country calls itself socialist that's
enough and then i'm like well what about
nazi germany and he's like
well no it's like well what do you mean
uh yeah i don't know i should have
cracked it on bezos
overall you're happy with the results of
the debate um yeah i think if i could
have
wished for anything else i think i wish
that lance would have stepped in more
and
forced him to answer questions i really
truly don't believe that
wolfe answered almost anything that i
asked directly
um and it felt weird for me to step in
and interrupt him when we had a
moderator present i don't know if i
would have
um yeah i don't know
lance did start stepping in he stepped
in twice which i was surprised about but
i wish we could have talked about the
boom bust cycle more too there's some i
wish we could have talked about anything
in this conversation
people said that boom bust cycles are
like inherent to capitalism i consider
that a feature instead of a negative
i think that one thing that i i should
have these studies in one hand
um one thing i've read that capitalist
countries are able to do more
effectively than socialist countries is
capitalist countries are really good at
responding to crises
so a crisis happens in a capitalist
country but it doesn't [ __ ] destroy
the capital's country
you have a bust but then you have a boom
again like capitalist countries boom and
bust
but then they rebound right which is
we've seen this happen several times you
know for him to point out like oh well
look at the great depression like oh
it's like oh cool well look where we are
now our country still exists where's the
ussr
you know where are some of these other
socialist regimes that have come and
gone uh throughout history you know our
you know
you failed at destroying wolf to end the
lefty arc every left in the internet
thanks to straight every lefty is always
gonna side with me i don't know where
i'll look to see how i feel like i did
in the middle i feel like my community
which still has a lot of lefty
sympathetic [ __ ] in it things that i
did really well which is good for me
um and then i'll have to try to dig
through discourse i don't know what
forms i'd look at later just to try to
gauge how i feel like i did maybe the
youtube comment section
or something but lefties are brain dead
so they're going to think that anybody
that is on the left automatically wins
anything
do you think saying you shouldn't
moralize your economic system as good
phrasing such warding because people
seem to interpret that as saying you
should be allowed to take your moral
actions again and
uh if somebody wants to talk about more
we can but
it also felt like he didn't really yeah
i think i've said this before he didn't
really engage with any of my points it
was more just he wanted to lecture i
guess but
yeah um
all right i'm going to
um i'm going to unmute doughnuts and
start responding everything david
pakman's community could be slightly
neutral no no no every
moderately left-leaning community on the
internet [ __ ] despises me because i'm
not as cuck socialist
including david pakman's david pakman's
community is pr is
massively over representing like
socialists at least in all their comment
sections other chats
it's insane but even pacman himself has
come out and said there are certain
things that he can't touch or talk about
because
this community is so far left leaning
do you think him not engaging in your
points was more ageism maybe he's used
to more formal structures of debate we
don't really have a back and forth but
you're just kind of lecturing the
audience but
what do you think about albert einstein
being a socialist i don't know is albert
einstein considered an inventor
one distinction that a lot of lefties
seem to have as well because albert
einstein has brought up so much
is there's a huge difference between
creating a theory
and using that theory to create an
applicable product that can be brought
to market
there's a big difference between coming
up with a theory and then coming up with
a product that can be water sold
lefties make this mistake a lot when um
lefties make this mistake a lot when
they talk about like oh well most
medical research is actually publicly
funded
that's great medical research does [ __ ]
all for the average person
what you need is a medical application
we can have all the research in the
world but if you don't actually have a
surgical procedure or a drug or
treatment or therapy then none of that
research means [ __ ] all
what you need at the end of the day and
what usually happens in private
enterprise is some company taking the
research and finding a way to apply it
to some therapy
without the application the research is
meaningless there's a lot of public
research that goes on and it's
incredibly valuable and that's awesome
but the public is not responsible for
bringing drugs to market that is an
incredibly arduous process
to figure out how do you pick winners
and losers which ironically not
ironically
which it actually makes sense is one of
the big problems
with um is one of the big problems with
uh
massively run co-op economies is that
the government
ends up being the one that has to pick
the winners and losers and historically
it's just been really hard to do this
back when yugoslavia was a thing basket
sent me a paper because yugoslavia tried
to do a market socialism thing
and it's a problem that a lot of like
heavily centrally planned economies have
is they can't respond to change as well
because there's so much bureaucracy in
the way
that trying to get like sectors of your
economy to adapt when you're not relying
on market signals is almost impossible
it was an issue in venezuela it was an
incident in yugoslavia before it's
dissolution
um yeah it's just it's just it's but i
mean it makes sense why this would be
the case it's just going to be
like free-flowing capital markets can
just allocate capital to different
sectors so [ __ ] quickly we see this
happen right
you're seeing pretty right and left at
the same time like you want equitable
distribution of resources but you're
against any significant systemic changes
could you
elaborate a bit on your specific qualm
with the form of socialism that richard
wolf advocates for similarly exclusively
democratization workplace because i
don't think that democratizing a
workplace
necessarily makes that workplace better
i think that a lot of lefties
i i just don't i don't believe that's
the case i'm sorry like
i've had work experience before this
jesus [ __ ] i don't want a lot of my
coworkers voting on what the [ __ ]
happened to my particular workplace
uh that might just be me or whatever but
um yeah i don't know i think that there
are cases where democratizing parts of
the workplace can be positive where the
workplace maybe could suit the worker
better
that's awesome but i would like to find
ways to incorporate that in our current
structure rather than
force it to be that like private
investment has disallowed
in some society you know like
people are upset right now because p you
know it's funny because wolfe was so
upset
that the democrats haven't enacted as
much left-leaning policy as they have in
the united states well what is the case
for that right
it's because of the american voter but
now you want the american voter to be in
charge of every single workplace you
want the same people that voted donald
trump into office to also be voting on
whether or not blacks and whites are
treated equally at the worth
of the workplace and you can sit there
and argue well voters are changed
because of corporate control on blah
blah blah blah it's like okay well how
wouldn't that happen in the workplace as
well how do you think that there
wouldn't be people that are wielding
influence to influence but right these
problems are
are endemic to people not endemic to
economic systems
evils like bigotry and slavery and
homophobia and transphobia and all this
stuff these these exist
independent of any economic system they
can exist under capitalism feudalism
socialism
anarchism uh monarchism whatever ism you
want
deadbeat dadaism
can you still be more specific about how
you thought he was moralizing his
position socialism i missed the opening
of the debate
um because the idea that there is an
employee and an employer i don't think
that that relationship is inherently
wrong i don't think that relationship is
inherently immoral and i think to just
moralize it and say you win the argument
because you said that's wrong i don't i
think that has to be demonstrated
we could go back and have a philosophy
debate on that because that's largely a
philosophy
that's wholly a philosophical assertion
but i reject that i i would argue
against it
just because somebody provides you
capital and you add some labor to it
that doesn't give you 100 ownership over
the
drop of labor added to some capital all
of a sudden gives you ownership over the
final product that's produced i would
argue that i would argue that on a
philosophical level
um but i i don't know if lefties have
ever even thought about having those
arguments
um the idea that adding a drop of labor
to or a bit of labor to capital or uh
natural resource
all of a sudden gives you an entitlement
100 to the newly created product
i think is ridiculous just as ridiculous
as saying the capitalist ought to own it
and the laborer gets no pay for it
i don't know i love the socialists using
his academic credentials as it does yeah
i didn't want to
he said it in the earlier part of the
bit if he would have brought that up in
the last part like i teach classes
like i would have reminded him you teach
undergraduate courses occasionally like
that's
like you're basically teaching glorified
high school classes like let's chill on
the [ __ ] credentials bro okay
but but but he brought that up i think
earlier in the debate and i didn't want
to be like super combative about that
you know
he was wrong about democrats not making
progress after the 30s you could have
brought up on medicare medicaid civil
rights were all passed in the 60s
section 8 was passed in 74.
your own income tax rate was 75 oh sure
yeah [ __ ] there there were like so many
different things that i wanted to but
the problem is we couldn't settle on any
issue i tried to say in the beginning
can we just go point by point but i
don't think it's stuck
um the problem is like any question i
would ask you'd say like point a b
c d e f g and i'm like well okay let's
talk about point a oh thanks
let's talk a little bit about point a
and then he'd be like oh okay well let
me respond to a
one two three four five six seven eight
nine ten it's like wait okay well let's
talk about a1
and he'd be like oh okay so a1 xyz
i was like [ __ ] me dude like right it's
just like i don't want to call i don't
want to use a debate bro term right but
it is a little gish galloping i can't
respond to every single point because
when i ask for clarification on one
thing we have to talk about 35 other
things
you know which damages my it gives it
makes him look more authoritative in the
conversation
in his three definitions of socialism it
sounded like anything that isn't and cap
is socialism yeah
that first definition of socialism that
he gave was so unbelievably wide
thanks it's like well [ __ ] me like what
am i
i mean like your definition of socialism
includes private enterprise
wait what the [ __ ] is this what the f
how the [ __ ] am i supposed to argue with
that your private enterprise
and your socialism wait what the [ __ ]
you have owners and employees i don't
even know what the [ __ ] i'm supposed to
say
to that like what the [ __ ] like you you
win you like auto won the debate
like everything is socialism basically
ah
do socialist economies have debt markets
um
yeah i think i read about this on the
venezuela example and the paper boss get
linked me uh
they have debt markets but those debt
markets are also oh what [ __ ] what was i
um what was i reading was it the eel
lecture we listened to
the interesting problem that you run
into with debt markets
is that a co-op could theoretically make
itself out to be um could make itself
out to be
like a like a capitalist structure
um hold on i'm trying to see where i
read this
[ __ ] i don't remember where i read this
um the summary of this is basically
let's say that you have one co-op that
runs a grocery store and then another
co-op that runs banks
let's say that you go to the bank co-op
you're like hey we need to get you know
a loan for our business because we want
to buy more buildings or whatever
then that co-op can essentially say like
oh sure well we're going to own part of
your business
if you do it or you're going to owe us
part of the what you produce you're
going to get royalties or something like
oh okay
well now you've just recreated
capitalism with more steps now you have
an owner class the bank that bank co-op
becomes the owners of part of the
business of the uh of the employee-owned
co-op right
that is now has part employee ownership
[ __ ] i wish i could just talk about
capital markets for like 10 minutes with
a lefty because i feel like wolf was
just totally like
absolutely like like the reality is
let me explain this real quick okay in
case you guys didn't understand this so
some of you um yeah maybe maybe
some of you guys don't understand this
if i invest in a company
i have part ownership in that company
and there are other investors in that
company
when that company makes decisions it
should be making decisions for the
benefit of its investors it has a
fiduciary responsibility
why is that the reason why that is is
because if it didn't have that
responsibility to outside investors or
shareholders
the problem is that they could just [ __ ]
off with all the money and say [ __ ] it
right
so here's the problem let's say there's
a 100 employee company and let's say
that this company wants to raise a [ __ ]
ton of money for expansion let's say
that i can say oh okay i'll donate
i'll uh i'll invest 10 million dollars
in your company's like oh really okay
well you get non-controlling shares
we'll give you 20 we're doing our
valuation you get 20
non-controlling shares there you go now
you own 20 of our co-op oh cool
then let's say the cop is like hey guys
we just got all this money
uh we're literally not expanding [ __ ]
all we're just gonna pay 80
out um to all of the employees in in the
form of like wages or whatever like
get [ __ ] well as a private capital
investor now you're like
oh well [ __ ] me i guess like
why the [ __ ] would you ever invest into
a co-op that gives you non-controlling
shares
why would you ever do that you're like i
don't want to do that i'm only going to
invest in companies that guarantee a
return
or that should be making a good faith
effort to provide a return to people
that are shareholders
like he kept saying that you were making
[ __ ] up yeah i know he started making
sure but this underlies every single
capital investment in all of
a capitalist society you have to be
otherwise nobody would invest in any
project ever because people just take
your money and run with it and when
people takes your money take your money
and run with it they usually get [ __ ]
prosecuted by the government you gotta
let it do that look what i'm gonna
[ __ ] march
when i'm gonna end run when you commit
fraud like that and you steal people's
money you get [ __ ] for it you're not
allowed to do that
um yeah
[ __ ]
wait so how do co-ops exist now co-ops
exist now
but a big problem with co-ops which i
acknowledged
exists in which everybody should a big
problem with co-ops is directly related
to the problem that i'm giving
and the problem is that co-ops have a
hard time raising capital because who
the [ __ ] is going to invest in a co-op
now there are some forms of investment
where i'll give you this much money and
you give me a royalty like on future
sales or something you can do that
but equity problems or cap initial
capital funding problems for
um co-ops are a big deal it's hard it's
really hard to start a club if i want to
start a business
i've got to find 10 other people that
have a [ __ ] ton of money that are all
willing to come in evenly with me or
somewhat evenly so that we can like
start a business together because
raising outside capital is so [ __ ]
hard
with uh with co-ops it's a problem that
they face it's not that's not like
something i invented like you can you
can go read up like co-op problems and
um capital issues are one of the first
things that comes up
why are co-ops not good options for
investors
because a co-op is owned by the workers
so the co-op is going to be maximizing
returns and profits for the workers i
don't want to buy into that as an
investor
because if i'm not a worker there i have
no guarantee that you're going to return
any profit to me
i invested in a co-op and got fresh eggs
every morning in return
there's no guarantee regardless of what
you're investing in for a privately held
company that it has
like shareholders there's they're
supposed to make a good faith effort to
return money to you
because that's where the decision making
comes from like the board of directors
and everything right
for a co-op it's just workers voting on
things
the owned by workers definition of
co-ops is not what both says right he
just cares about workers control i mean
it's the same thing i mean he dances
around it it's hard to get him to commit
to like any particular thing
i don't know
[ __ ] i should be eating this in my hands
why did he argue that not all co-ops are
worker owned um
because like i don't know because
everything could because his system was
ultimately flexible
i felt like he was saying that a cop
doesn't have to be owned 100 of the
workers
a socialist economy could have private
investment in enterprise
like we don't necessarily need the
government to disa lot like i don't know
just like
basically socialism was everything like
that's what it that's what it felt like
yeah i don't know [ __ ] it
also i feel like i didn't respond
adequately to my because i looked up
mom
china has hasn't had an explosion of
growth
in terms of their um like gdp per capita
sure but when did that growth happen
china gdp per capita history china
opened itself up to massive foreign
investment
in like the 90s
when do we see the explosion of growth
right
it doesn't happen until um
i don't know how far back i can get this
graph to go but this [ __ ] is [ __ ]
flatlined sometimes
negative right it seems like it wasn't
until it started to open itself up to
massive foreign investment and it
started to liberalize its economy more
that all of a sudden china saw these
massive growths in gdp
that's what i saw right also i [ __ ] i'm
not 100 sure this i wish i um
my understanding is that japan uh
japan's growth was superior to that of
russia or the ussr
[ __ ] i need to go and look that up at
some point you give socialism credit for
that though yeah but it wasn't until
they
liberalized their economy that i don't
know the foreign direct investment the
fdi for china has been like a massive
driver of its growth i don't think
anybody
he also said that they invested because
china had an educated population even
though
half the country couldn't read in the
80s oh yeah and then him trying to say
that like
people went to china because of like a
cheap labor for dude that almost sounded
like a self-owned
but i didn't get to push him because he
went on for like 12 minutes he was like
no that's not true people actually
wanted to come to china because there's
a lot of people willing to work for
cheap like
what how is this is that are you
supporting your argument or my are you
basically saying that other countries go
to china and exploit their labor force
and that's like a big win for china [ __ ]
but [ __ ] me whatever
oh yeah eric the trade relationships
helped a lot as well when china began to
take its foreign trade more seriously
for sure
dsp got unpartnered oh no
uh oh
oh [ __ ] stocked unless twitter
following who's not impressed with
wolves performance
these are the types of comments that i
look for to know that i did
very well when somebody says it was a
deeply unsatisfying debate i don't think
destiny comes out of this looking better
but i thought wolf didn't really look
good when i see comments like that made
by people that i know
[ __ ] hate me then i usually feel like
oh okay i think i did
i probably did really well in this
conversation that's usually like because
i'll see the types of things on like um
4chan
where people will be like even though
destiny is like a bisexual cuck
whatever like words people call me like
i think that this wasn't the best
showing for lauren southern or sorry
when i read comments like that usually i
know that the conversation went really
well for me
does sdl hate you no i think me and
stockton left are good his community
hates me though
every single left-leaning community
[ __ ] hates me there's not a single
exception to that
on the internet unironically i'm not
even being hyperbolic
i feel like lance asked him that
question and what wolf was supposed to
say well of course you'd have your ps5s
and your other luxury goods and any
socialist society
all of the workers would collectively be
agreeing to make these goods and
services for one another the difference
is
is that when we produce ps5s the average
worker is the one that's getting
rewarded for that not some technocratic
bureaucratic person way at the end some
owner-class person
at the end of the line i feel like that
was supposed to be wolves answer so of
course you get your goods and services
but now when you buy a ps5 you know that
money is going into the hands of the
workers that made it
not some not some owner that's way past
the line of not even having to do
anything with the production of it i
feel like that was the answer he's
supposed to give
but then he was like well i don't know
you'd have to go debate your worker into
going to
to work to make one for you overall i
think your interruptions of wolf were
kind of annoying
just comes off as needlessly aggressive
but i agree that
moralizing socialism is stupid they
can't
or don't know how to make economic
arguments so they default to capitalism
bad
i felt like i had to interrupt because
he was like he was going on for so
long like i was getting gish gallop so
[ __ ] hard he would bring up like 30
things
i'm sorry i interrupted the donut like
holy [ __ ] i was getting steamrolled
and then he was trying to interrupt me
what i was trying to answer [ __ ]
don't feel bad destiny this was not a
debate
he just rambled and ignored your points
you sort of gave up by the end so it
came off as you accepting defeat
so he came across as the winner without
making any concrete points
uh i don't know about that yeah wolf was
speaking during my closing statement
true
um do you think referring to him as
professors a little past progressive
um i tried not to actually i i
maybe i should have i should have
actually no i should have asked at the
beginning i thought that you were
supposed to refer to a professor as
professor
um like i don't know i can't call him
richard
and addressing him as mr wolfe i think
sounds also
um kind of weird i thought i thought it
was like professor the professor
i thought that's like how you're
supposed to like unironically how you're
supposed to refer to somebody that has a
phd
that's my understanding i don't know how
else i would um
would refer to him as getting him into
exchanges where he is forced to actually
address what you say without lecturing
for minutes at a time is much better
conversation
then he talks to you instead of lectures
if you slash
yeah that's what i try to do but i don't
think we ever got to do that it's really
really hard i had the same problem with
the pogen guy
we're like can we just have like a
real-life conversation where we go back
and forth and get to the bottom of this
particular thing rather than it feeling
like i'm on a prime case panel
where every person just wants to come on
and like give like their four-minute
monologue and not respond to anything
other person said
i wish that uh i wish that he would have
i wish that we could have gone back and
forth on a point more concretely
i think that rhetorically i think i was
relatively effective i don't think he
brought up anything that i wasn't ready
to respond to like i didn't get
blindsided from anything
um i think that was just a matter a
matter of like managing the conversation
uh i think that there were some things
that sucked but i don't know like
reasonably what was in my power to do
things about
um like when somebody wants to ramble
that much and there's a moderator
present doesn't stop
i don't know what i can do in that case
um i tried to hold him down to an answer
but i don't think we ever
got there we what did we go back and
forth we went back and forth on
something oh we didn't have a response
to it i don't know if that landed
well that um like i'm more
what did i say i'm more comfortable
blaming chernobyl on socialism than i am
blaming the coronavis pandemic on
capitalism
he didn't have any response to that and
i feel like if he would have had a
strong response that i feel like he
would have cut in and given one can you
clarify the japan vs ussr growth
rebuttal you made
uh i don't think that the massive growth
of the ussr came under the soviet union
but i'm not 100 i didn't know i didn't
know he's going to defend the soviet
union so much i thought he largely
disowns the soviet union [ __ ]
because usually i think what we heard
him in the base he's like he's just like
oh i'm not talking about the soviet
union i don't think we heard him defend
the soviet union so much
my understanding is that japan had more
growth um over the soviet union the
soviet union did
um and then [ __ ] and then i've heard
like i've got like collections of facts
but i haven't put them all together
because i just don't know much about
like the history like the founding of
the soviet new river
um the cheshire uh cat guy diamond he
said russia was europe's third largest
economy behind britain and germany by
the year 1913.
um france was poorer than the soviet
union as was the dutch republic and
belgium all of which manage not to
masturbate to their own populations with
poor economic planning
so yeah [ __ ] i i just i don't know the
comparative conditions in the early
early 1900s across europe
to compare to the start of the ussr um
but after this disappointing showing
from wolff you should definitely debate
david friedman
he would give definitions cogent
arguments and be much more charitable in
general
i know you don't want to debate in caps
but you should give it a shot
okay destiny why aren't more people just
social democrats
it seems most people rightfully take
issue with exploitation but you don't
need to be a socialist and abolish
capitalism to fix
the problem remember to hit that like
and subscribe and don't forget the
notification bell so that my videos show
up
right in your feed